<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The paradyse of daynty deuises aptly furnished, with sundry pithie and learned inuentions: deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwards, sometimes of her Maiesties chappel: the rest, by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honour, and woorshippe. viz. S. Barnarde. E.O. L. Vaux. D.S. Iasper Heyvvood. F.K. M. Bevve. R. Hill. M. Yloop, vvith others.</title>
            <author>Edwards, Richard, 1523?-1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105445</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 337:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The paradyse of daynty deuises aptly furnished, with sundry pithie and learned inuentions: deuised and written for the most part, by M. Edwards, sometimes of her Maiesties chappel: the rest, by sundry learned gentlemen, both of honour, and woorshippe. viz. S. Barnarde. E.O. L. Vaux. D.S. Iasper Heyvvood. F.K. M. Bevve. R. Hill. M. Yloop, vvith others.</title>
                  <author>Edwards, Richard, 1523?-1566.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [R. Jones for?] Henry Disle, dwellyng in Paules Churchyard, at the south west doore of Saint Paules Church, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name conjectured by STC; there is a change in typography at F1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE PARADYSE</hi> of daynty deuiſes, <hi>aptly furniſhed,
with ſundry pithie and learned inuentions:</hi> deuiſed and written for the
most part, by M. Edwards, ſometimes of her Maiesties Chappel: the rest, by
ſundry learned Gentlemen, both of honor, and woorſhippe. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>S. Barnarde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>E. O.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>L. Vaux.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>D. S.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iaſper Heyvvood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>F. K.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>M. Bevve.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>R. Hill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>M. Yloop, vvith others.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>EGO SVM VIA ET VERITAS</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by Henry Diſle, dwellyng in
<hi>Paules Churchyard, at the South weſt doore</hi> of Saint Paules Church,
and are there to be ſolde. <hi>1576.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>IE NE CHERCHE Q'VNE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Syr Henry Compton Knight, <hi>Lorde
Compton, of Compton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONORABLE,</hi> and my very good Lord, (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming
vppon your curteſy) J am bolde to preſent vnto your honor, this ſmall
volume: Entituled, The Paradiſe of deynty deuiſes, being penned by diuers
learned Gentlemen, and collected togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through the trauell of one, both
of woorſhip and credite, for his priuate vſe: who not long ſince departed
this lyfe, which when J had peruſed ouer, not with out the aduiſe of
ſundry my freendes, J determined by theyr good motion, to ſet them in
print, who thervnto greatly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me, with theſe and like woordes: The
wryters of them, were both of honor and worſhip: beſides that, our owne
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men, and ſuch as for theyr learnyng and grauitie, might be
accounted of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:5735:3"/> the wiſeſt. Furthermore, the ditties both pithy
and pleaſant, aſwell for the inuention as meter, and wyll yeelde a farre
greater delight, being as they are ſo aptly made to be ſet to any ſong in
<hi>.5.</hi> partes, or ſong to inſtrument. Which wel conſydering, J
purpoſed not to forſake ſo good an occaſion, beſeeching your honor to
accept it in good part, cheefely for the aucthours ſake: who though ſome of
them are departed this lyfe, yet theyr woorthy doings ſhall continue for
euer: for like as the ſhadow foloweth the body, ſo praiſe foloweth
vertue: and as the ſhadow goeth ſomtimes before, and ſometimes behind,
ſo doth praiſe alſo to vertue: but the later it commeth, the greater it
is, and to be the better eſteemed. Thus fearing to offende your honor with
theſe my rude ſpeaches, J end, wiſhing your L. many yeres of ioy.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your good Lordſhips wholy to commaund,</hi> H.
D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:3"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATION of the bleſsed Saint Barnards <hi>verſes,
conteynyng the vnſtable felicitie</hi> of this wayfaring worlde.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>CVR mundus militat, ſub vana gloria, cuius proſperitas
est tranſitoria;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tam cito labitur, eius potentia, quam vaſa figuli, quae
ſunt fragilia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>WHY dooth eache ſtate apply it ſelfe to worldly
prayſe?</l>
               <l>And vndertake ſuch toyle, to heape vp honours gayne:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſeate, though ſeeming ſure, on fickle fortune
ſtayes,</l>
               <l>Whoſe giftes were neuer proued, perpetuall to remayne.</l>
               <l>But euen as earthen pot, with euery fillip fayles,</l>
               <l>So fortunes fauour flittes, and fame with honour quayles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plus crede litteris, ſcriptis in glacie, quam mundi
fragilis, vanae fallaciae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fallax in premijs, virtutis ſpecie, quae nunquam habuit,
tempus fiduciae.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke rather firme to finde, a figure grauen in Iſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſubſtance ſubiect is, to heate of ſhinyng
ſunne:</l>
               <l>Then hope for ſtedfaſt ſtay, in wanton worldes
deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fained fond delightes, from falſheds forge doo
come.</l>
               <l>And vnder Vertues veyle, are largely dealt about,</l>
               <l>Deceiuing thoſe, who thinke their date wyll neuer out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Magis credendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est viris fallacibus, quam mundi miſeris
proſperitatibus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Falſis inſanijs &amp; voluptatibus, falſis quoquae
studiis &amp; vanitatibus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The trifeling truethles tongue, of rumours lying lippes,</l>
               <l>Deſerues more truſt, then dooth the higheſt happy hap:</l>
               <l>That world to worldlinges geues, for ſee how honour
ſlippes,</l>
               <l>To fooliſhe fond cenceytes, to pleaſures poyſoned
ſap.</l>
               <l>To ſtudyes falſe in proofe, to artes applyed to gayne,</l>
               <l>To fickle fancies toyes, which wyſedome deemeth vayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5735:4"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic vbi Salomon, olim tam nobilis? vel vbi Samſon est, dux
inuincibilis?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vel dulcis Ionathas, multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amabilis? vel pulcher Abſolon,
vultu mirabilis?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where is the ſacred king, that Salomon the wyſe?</l>
               <l>Whoſe wyſdome, former time, of duetie did commend:</l>
               <l>Where is that Samſon ſtrong, that monſtrous man in
ſyze?</l>
               <l>Whoſe forced arme, dyd cauſe the mighty pillers bend.</l>
               <l>Where is the peareles Prince, the freendly Ionathas?</l>
               <l>Or Abſolon, whoſe ſhape and fauour did ſurpaſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quo Caeſar abijt, celſus imperio, vel diues
ſplendidus, totus in prandie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dic vbi Tullius, clarus eloquio, vel Aristoteles, ſummus
ingenio.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where is that Caeſar nowe, whoſe hygh renowmed fame,</l>
               <l>Of ſundry conqueſtes wonne, throughout the world did
ſound?</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Diues</hi> riche in ſtore, and rich in richely
name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe cheſt with gold and diſhe, with daynties did
abound.</l>
               <l>Where is the paſſing grace, of <hi>Tullies</hi> pleding
ſkill?</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Aristotles</hi> vayne, whoſe penne had witte and
wyll.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O eſca vermium, ò maſsa pulueris, ò ros,
ò vanitas, cur ſic extolleris?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignoras penitus vtrum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ras vixeris, fac bonum omnibus, quam
diu poteris.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O foode of filthy woorme, oh lumpe of lothſome clay,</l>
               <l>O life full like the deawe, which mornyng ſunne dooth
waſte:</l>
               <l>O ſhadowe vayne, whoſe ſhape with ſunne dooth ſhrinke
away,</l>
               <l>Why gloryeſt thou ſo much, in honour to be plaſte?</l>
               <l>Sith that no certayne houre, of life thou doſt enioy,</l>
               <l>Moſt fyt it were, thy tyme in goodneſſe to employ.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam breue festu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est, haec mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di gloria, vt vmbra hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
ſic eius gaudia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae ſemper ſubtrahit aeterna praemia, &amp; ducunt
hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ad dura deuia.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How ſhort a banquet ſeemes the pompe of high renowme?</l>
               <l>How like the ſenſeles ſhape, of ſhiuering ſhadowe
thinne?</l>
               <l>Are wanton worldly toyes, whoſe pleaſure plucketh downe,</l>
               <l>Our harts from hope, &amp; hands from works, which heauen
ſhould win.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5735:4"/>And takes vs from the trod, which guides to endles
gayne,</l>
               <l>And ſets vs in the way, that leades to laſtyng payne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haec mundi gloria, quae magnipenditur, ſacris in litteris,
flos faeni dicitur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vt leue folium, quod vento rapitur, ſic vita hominem, hac
vita tollitur.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The pompe of worldly prayſe, which worldlinges hold ſo
deere,</l>
               <l>In holy ſacred booke, is likened to a flowre:</l>
               <l>Whoſe date dooth not conteyne, a weeke, a moonth, or
yeere,</l>
               <l>But ſpringing nowe, dooth fade againe within an houre.</l>
               <l>And as the lighteſt leafe, with winde about is throwne,</l>
               <l>So lyght is lyfe of man, and lightly hence is blowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Finis. My Lucke is loſſe.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Beware of had I wyst.</head>
            <l>BEware of had I wyſt, whoſe fine bringes care and ſmart,</l>
            <l>Eſteeme of all as they deſerue, and deeme as deemd thou
art:</l>
            <l>So ſhall thy perfect freend, enioy his hoped hyre,</l>
            <l>And faythleſſe fawning foe, ſhall miſſe theffect of his
deſyre.</l>
            <l>Good wyll ſhall haue his gayne, and hate ſhal heape
deſpite,</l>
            <l>A faithleſſe freend ſhall finde diſtruſt, and loue
ſhall reape delight.</l>
            <l>Thy ſelfe ſhall reſt in peace, thy freend ſhall ioy thy
fate,</l>
            <l>Thy foe ſhall fret at thy good happe, and I ſhall ioy thy
ſtate.</l>
            <l>But this my fond aduiſe, may ſeeme perchaunce but vayne,</l>
            <l>As rather teaching how to loſe, then howe a freend to gayne.</l>
            <l>But this not my intent, to teache to finde a freend,</l>
            <l>But ſafely how to loue and leaue, is all that I entend.</l>
            <l>And yf you prooue in part, and finde my counſell true,</l>
            <l>Then wyſhe me well for my good wyll, tis all I craue adewe.</l>
            <trailer>Finis. My lucke is loſſe.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:5"/>
            <head>The perfect tryall of a faythfull freend.</head>
            <l>NOt ſtayed ſtate, but feeble ſtay,</l>
            <l>Not coſtly robes, but bare aray:</l>
            <l>Not paſſed wealth, but preſent want,</l>
            <l>Not heaped ſtore, but ſclender ſkant:</l>
            <l>Not plenties purſe, but poore eſtate,</l>
            <l>Not happy happe, but froward fate:</l>
            <l>Not wyſhe at wyll, but want of ioy,</l>
            <l>Not harts good health, but hartes annoy:</l>
            <l>Not freedomes vſe, but priſons thrall,</l>
            <l>Not coſtly ſeate, but loweſt fall:</l>
            <l>Not weale I meane, but wretched woe,</l>
            <l>Dooth truely trye, the freend from foe:</l>
            <l>And nought, but froward fortune proues,</l>
            <l>Who fawning faines, or ſimply loues.</l>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yloop.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>No pleaſure, without ſome payne.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SWeete were the ioyes, that both might like and laſt,</l>
               <l>Strange were the ſtate, exempt from all diſtreſſe:</l>
               <l>Happy the lyfe, that no miſhap ſhould taſt,</l>
               <l>Bleſſed the chaunce, might neuer change ſucceſſe.</l>
               <l>Were ſuch a lyfe to leade, or ſtate to proue,</l>
               <l>Who would not wyſhe, that ſuch a lyfe were loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But O the ſowry ſauce of ſweete vnſure,</l>
               <l>When pleaſures flye, and flee with waſt of winde:</l>
               <l>The truſtleſſe traynes that hoping hartes allure,</l>
               <l>When ſweete delightes doo but allure the minde.</l>
               <l>When care conſumes and waſtes the wretched wight,</l>
               <l>Whyle fancy feedes, and drawes of her delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What lyfe were loue, yf loue were free from payne?</l>
               <l>But O that payne, with pleaſure matcht ſhould meete:</l>
               <l>Why dyd the courſe of nature ſo ordayne,</l>
               <l>That ſugred ſowre, muſt ſauſe the bitter ſweete.</l>
               <l>Which ſowre from ſweete, might any meanes remoue.</l>
               <l>What happe, what heauen, what lyfe, were lyke to loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5735:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Our pleaſures are vanities.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BEhold the</hi> blaſt which blowes, the bloſſomes
from the tree,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The end</hi> whereof conſumes and comes, to nought we
ſee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ere thou</hi> therefore be blowen, from life that may not
laſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Begin</hi> for grace, to call for time miſpent and
paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haue mind</hi> on brittle life, whoſe pleaſures are
but vayne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On death</hi> likewyſe bethinke, how thou maiſt not
remaine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And feare</hi> thy Lord to greene, which ſought thy
ſoule to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſynne</hi> no more be bent, but mercie aſke and
haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For death</hi> who dooth not ſpare, the kinges on earth
to kill,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall reape</hi> alſo from thee, thy pleaſure, life,
and will.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That lyfe</hi> which yet remaynes, and in thy breſt
appeares,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath ſowne</hi> in thée ſutch ſeedes, you
ought to weede with teares.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And life</hi> that ſhall ſucceede, when death is worne
and paſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall ſpring</hi> for euer then, in ioy or paine to
laſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where death</hi> on life hath power ye ſee, that life
alſo,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath mowen</hi> the fruites of death, which neuer more
ſhall growe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> M. Edwardes MAY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen <hi>MAY</hi> is in his prime, then <hi>MAY</hi> eche hart
reioyce,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> bedeckes eche branch w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greene, eche bird
ſtreines forth his voyce.</l>
                  <l>The liuely ſappe creepes, vp into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloming thorne,</l>
                  <l>The flowres, which cold in priſon kept, now laughes the
froſt to ſcorne.</l>
                  <l>All natures Impes triumphes, whyles ioyfull May dooth
laſt,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, of all the yeere the pleaſant
time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> makes the cherfull hue, <hi>MAY</hi> breedes and
bringes newe blood,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> marcheth throughout euery limme, <hi>MAY</hi>
makes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mery moode.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>MAY</hi> pricketh tender hartes, their warbling notes to
tune,</l>
                  <l>Ful ſtrange it is, yet ſome wee ſee, doo make their
<hi>MAY</hi> in <hi>Iune.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus thinges are ſtraungely wrought, whyles ioyfull
<hi>MAY</hi> doth laſt,</l>
                  <l>Take <hi>MAY</hi> in time, when <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, the
pleaſant time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5735:6"/>
                  <l>All ye that liue on earth, and haue your <hi>MAY</hi> at
wyll,</l>
                  <l>Reioyce in <hi>MAY,</hi> as I doo now, and vſe your
<hi>MAY</hi> with ſkill.</l>
                  <l>Vſe <hi>MAY,</hi> whyle that you may, for <hi>MAY</hi> hath
but his time,</l>
                  <l>When all the fruite is gone, it is to late the tree to
clime.</l>
                  <l>Your liking and your luſt, is freſhe whyles <hi>MAY</hi>
dooth laſt,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>MAY</hi> is gone, of all the yeere the pleaſaunt
time is paſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Faire woordes make fooles faine.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN youthfull yeeres when fyrſt my young deſyres began,</l>
                  <l>To pricke mee foorth to ſerue in Court a ſclender tall
young man.</l>
                  <l>My Fathers bleſſing then I aſkt vpon my knee,</l>
                  <l>Who bleſſing me with trembling hand, theſe woordes gan
ſay to me.</l>
                  <l>My ſonne, God guide thy way, and ſhielde thee from
miſchaunce,</l>
                  <l>And make thy iuſt deſartes in Court, thy poore eſtate to
aduaunce.</l>
                  <l>Yet when thou art become one of the Courtly trayne,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on this prouerbe olde (qd he) that faire woordes make
fooles faine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This counſell grauely geuen, moſt ſtrange appeares to
me.</l>
                  <l>Tyll tract of time, with open eyes, had made me plainely
ſee.</l>
                  <l>What ſubtill ſleightes are wrought, by painted tales
deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>When hollowe hartes with freendly ſhoes the ſimple doo
entiſe.</l>
                  <l>To thinke al golde that ſhines to feede their fonde
deſire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſhiuering cold is warmd with ſmoke, in ſtead of
flaming fire.</l>
                  <l>Sith talke of tickle truſt, dooth breede a hope moſt
vaine,</l>
                  <l>This prouerbe true by proofe I finde, that faire woordes make
fooles faine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faire ſpeache alway doeth well, where deedes inſue faire
woordes,</l>
                  <l>Faire ſpeache againe, alway dooth euil, that buſſhes
geues for birdes.</l>
                  <l>Who hopes to haue fayre woordes, to trye his luckie lot,</l>
                  <l>If I may counſel let him ſtrike it, whyle the iron is
hotte.</l>
                  <l>But them that feede on cloddes, in ſteade of pleaſaunt
grapes,</l>
                  <l>And after warning often geuen, for better lucke ſtill
gapes.</l>
                  <l>Full loth I am, yet muſt I tell them in woordes plaine,</l>
                  <l>This prouerbe old proues true in them, that faire words makes
fooles faine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5735:6"/>
                  <l>Wo woorth the time that woordes, ſo ſlowly turne to
deedes,</l>
                  <l>Wo worth the time, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faire ſweete floures, are growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to
rotten weedes.</l>
                  <l>But thriſe wo woorth the time, that trueth, away is
fled,</l>
                  <l>Wherein I ſee how ſimple hartes, with woordes are vainely
fed.</l>
                  <l>Truſt no faire woordes therefore, where no deedes doo
enſue,</l>
                  <l>Truſt words, as ſkilful Falkeners doo truſt Haukes that
neuer flew.</l>
                  <l>Truſt deedes, let wodrdes be woordes, which neuer wrough me
gaine,</l>
                  <l>Let my experience make you wyſe, and let woordes make fooles
faine.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> In his extreame ſyckneſſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>What greeues my bones, and makes my body faint?</l>
                  <l>What prickes my fleſh and teares my head in twaayne?</l>
                  <l>Why doo I wake, when reſt ſhould me attaynt?</l>
                  <l>When others laugh, why doo I liue in paine?</l>
                  <l>I <hi>toſſe</hi> I <hi>turne,</hi> I <hi>change</hi> from
ſide to ſide,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>ſtretche</hi> me oft, in ſorowes linkes
betyde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I <hi>toſſe,</hi> as one betoſt in waues of care,</l>
                  <l>I <hi>turne,</hi> to flee the woes of lothſome lyfe:</l>
                  <l>I <hi>change</hi> to ſpie, yf death this corps might
ſpare,</l>
                  <l>I <hi>ſtretche</hi> to heauen, to ridde me of this
ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Thus doo I <hi>ſtretche</hi> and <hi>change,</hi> and
<hi>toſſe</hi> and <hi>turne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whyle I in hope of heauen by life doo burne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then holde thee ſtill, let be thy heauineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Aboliſhe care, forgeat thy pining woe:</l>
                  <l>For by this meanes ſoone ſhalt thou finde
redreſſe,</l>
                  <l>When oft betoſt, hence thou to heauen muſt goe.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>toſſe</hi> and <hi>turne,</hi> and
<hi>tumble</hi> franke and free.</l>
                  <l>O happy thryſe, when thou in heauen ſhalt be.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="subpart">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:5735:7"/>
               <head>5. For Christmas day.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <l>Reioyce reioyce, with hart and voyce.</l>
                  <l>In Christes birth this day reioyce.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRom Virgins wombe, this day dyd ſpring,</l>
                  <l>The precious ſeede that onely ſaued man:</l>
                  <l>This day let man reioyce and ſweetely ſing,</l>
                  <l>Since on this day ſaluation fyrſt began.</l>
                  <l>This day dyd Chriſte mans ſoule from death remooue,</l>
                  <l>With glorious ſaintes to dwell in heauen aboue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This day to man came pledge of perfect peace,</l>
                  <l>This day to man came loue and vnitie:</l>
                  <l>This day mans greefe began for to ſurceaſe,</l>
                  <l>This day did man receyue a remedie.</l>
                  <l>For eche offence, and euery deadly ſinne,</l>
                  <l>With guiltie hart, that erſt he wandred in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Chriſtes flocke, let loue be ſurely plaſte,</l>
                  <l>From Chriſtes flocke, let concorde hate expell:</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſtes flocke, let loue be ſo embraſte,</l>
                  <l>As we in Chriſte, and Chriſte in vs may dwell.</l>
                  <l>Chriſte is the aucthour of all vnitie,</l>
                  <l>From whence proceedeth all felicitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſyng vnto this glittering glorious king,</l>
                  <l>O prayſe his name, let euery liuing thing:</l>
                  <l>Let hart and voyce like Belles of ſyluer ring,</l>
                  <l>The comfort that this day did bring.</l>
                  <l>Let Lute, let Shalme, with ſounde of ſweete delight,</l>
                  <l>The ioy of Chriſtes birth this day reſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="subpart">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5735:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Easter day.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALl mortall men this day reioyce,</l>
                  <l>In Chriſt that you redeemed hath:</l>
                  <l>By death, with death ſing we with voyce,</l>
                  <l>To him that hath appeſed Gods wrath.</l>
                  <l>Due vnto man for ſinfull path,</l>
                  <l>Wherein before he went aſtray:</l>
                  <l>Geue thankes to him with perfect faith,</l>
                  <l>That for mankind hath made this glorious day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This day he roſe from tombe againe,</l>
                  <l>Wherin his precious corſe was laide:</l>
                  <l>Whom cruelly the Iewes had ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>With blooddy woundes full ill araide.</l>
                  <l>O Man be nowe no more diſmaide,</l>
                  <l>If thou hencefoorth from ſinne doo ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Of death thou needeſt not be afraide,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt conquered death for this his glorious day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His death preuayled had no whit,</l>
                  <l>As Paul the Apoſtle well doth write,</l>
                  <l>Except he had vpryſen yet,</l>
                  <l>From death to life by Godlike might.</l>
                  <l>With moſt triumphant glittering light.</l>
                  <l>This day his glory ſhined I ſay,</l>
                  <l>And made vs bright as ſunne this glorious day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O man aryſe with Chriſte therefore,</l>
                  <l>Since he from ſinne hath made thee free:</l>
                  <l>Beware thou fall in ſinne no more,</l>
                  <l>But ryſe as Chriſte dyd ryſe for thee.</l>
                  <l>So mayſt thou him in glory ſee,</l>
                  <l>When he at day of doome ſhal ſay:</l>
                  <l>Come thou my childe and dwell with me,</l>
                  <l>God Graunt vs all, to ſee that glorious day.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iaſper Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="subpart">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5735:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> For Whitſunday.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COme holy ghoſt eternall God, and eaſe the wofull
greefe:</l>
                  <l>That thorough the heapes of heauy ſinne, can no where find
releefe.</l>
                  <l>Doo thou O God redreſſe</l>
                  <l>The great diſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>Of ſinfull heauineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come comfort the aflicted thoughtes, of my conſumed
hart:</l>
                  <l>O ryd the pearcing pricking paynes, of my tormenting
ſmart.</l>
                  <l>O holy Ghoſt graunt me</l>
                  <l>That I by thee</l>
                  <l>From ſinne may purged be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art my God, to thee alone,</l>
                  <l>I wyll commend my cauſe:</l>
                  <l>Not glittering golde nor precious ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Shall make me leaue thy lawes.</l>
                  <l>O teache me then the way</l>
                  <l>Whereby I may</l>
                  <l>Make thee my onely ſtay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My lippes, my tongue, my hart and al,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſpreade thy mightie name:</l>
                  <l>My voyce ſhall neuer ceaſe to ſound,</l>
                  <l>The prayſes of the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Yea euery liuing thing</l>
                  <l>Shall ſweetely ſyng</l>
                  <l>To thee (O heauenly king.)</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Kindlemarſh.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="subpart">
               <head>8.
<l>Who mindes to bring his ſhippe to happy ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Must care to knowe the lawes of wyſdomes lore.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY freend, yf thou wylt credite me in ought,</l>
                  <l>To whom the trueth by tryall well appeares:</l>
                  <l>Nought woorth is wit, till it be dearely bought,</l>
                  <l>There is no wyſedome but in hoaric heares.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5735:8"/>Yet yf I may of wyſedome oft define,</l>
                  <l>As well as others haue of happineſſe:</l>
                  <l>Then to my woordes my freende, thy eare encline,</l>
                  <l>The thinges that make thee wyſe, are theſe I
geſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Feare God, and knowe thy ſelfe in eche degree,</l>
                  <l>Be freend to all, familier but to fewe:</l>
                  <l>Too light of credite, ſee thou neuer be,</l>
                  <l>For tryall oft in truſt, dooth treaſon ſhewe.</l>
                  <l>To others faultes caſt not to much thy eye,</l>
                  <l>Accuſe no man of gilt, amend thy owne:</l>
                  <l>Of medling much, dooth miſchiefe oft aryſe,</l>
                  <l>And oft debate, by tickle tongue is ſowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What thing thou wylt haue hid, to none declare,</l>
                  <l>In woorde or deede, beware of had I wiſt:</l>
                  <l>So ſpend thy good, that ſome thou euer ſpare,</l>
                  <l>For freendes like Haukes, doo ſoare from emptie fiſt.</l>
                  <l>Cut out thy coate, according to thy cloth,</l>
                  <l>Suſpected perſons ſee thou alwayes flee:</l>
                  <l>Beleeue not him that once hath broke his troth,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet of gift, without deſart be free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Time quickly ſlips beware how thou it ſpend,</l>
                  <l>Of wanton youth, repentes a painefull age:</l>
                  <l>Beginne nothing without an eye to thend,</l>
                  <l>Nor bowe thyne eare from counſell of the ſage.</l>
                  <l>If thou to farre let out thy fancie ſlip,</l>
                  <l>And witleſſe wyll from reaſons rule outſtart:</l>
                  <l>Thy folly, ſhall at length be made thy whippe,</l>
                  <l>And ſore, the ſtripes of ſhame, ſhal cauſe thee
ſmart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To doo too much for olde men is but loſt,</l>
                  <l>Of freendſhip had to women comes like gaine:</l>
                  <l>Beſtowe not thou on children to much coſt,</l>
                  <l>For what thou dooeſt for theſe, is all in vayne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5735:9"/>The olde man or he can requite, he dyes,</l>
                  <l>Vnconſtant is the womans waueryng minde:</l>
                  <l>Full ſoone the boy thy freendſhip wyl deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>And him for loue thou ſhalt vngratefull finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The aged man is like the barren ground,</l>
                  <l>The woman like the Reede that wagges with winde:</l>
                  <l>There may no truſt in tender yeeres be found,</l>
                  <l>And of the three, the boy is moſt vnkinde.</l>
                  <l>If thou haue found a faithfull freend in deede.</l>
                  <l>Beware thou loſe not loue of ſuch a one:</l>
                  <l>He ſhall ſometime ſtand thee in better ſteede,</l>
                  <l>Then treaſure great of golde or precious ſtone.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iaſper Heywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of the vnconstant stay of fortunes giftes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF <hi>Fortune</hi> be thy ſtay, thy ſtate is very
tickle,</l>
                  <l>She beares a double face, diſguiſed, falſe, and
fickle.</l>
                  <l>This day ſhe ſeemes to ſmile, to morrowe wyl ſhe
frowne,</l>
                  <l>What nowe ſhe ſets aloft, anone ſhe throweth downe.</l>
                  <l>Fly <hi>Fortunes</hi> ſly deſeytes, let <hi>Vertue</hi> be
thy guide,</l>
                  <l>If that you doo intend in happy ſtate to bide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vpon the ſetled Rocke, thy building ſureſt
ſtandes,</l>
                  <l>Away it quickly weares, that reſteth on the ſandes.</l>
                  <l>Dame <hi>Vertue</hi> is the Rocke, that yeeldes aſſured
ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Dame <hi>Fortune</hi> is the Sand, that ſkowreth ſoone
away,</l>
                  <l>Chuſe that is certaine, let thinges vncertayne
paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Preferre the precious golde, before the brittle
glaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sly <hi>Fortune</hi> hath her ſleightes, ſhe plaies vpon
the packe,</l>
                  <l>Looke whom ſhe fauours moſt, at length ſhe turnes to
wracke.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Vertue</hi> ſimply deales, ſhe ſhuns deceitfull
trayne,</l>
                  <l>Who is by <hi>Fortune</hi> rayſed vp, ſhall neuer fall
againe.</l>
                  <l>Sticke faſt to <hi>Vertue</hi> then, that geues aſſured
truſt,</l>
                  <l>And fly from <hi>Fortunes</hi> freekes, that euer prooue
vniuſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="subpart">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5735:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Promiſe is debt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN my accompt, the promiſe that is vowed,</l>
                  <l>Among the good, is holden ſuch a debt:</l>
                  <l>As he is thought, no whit to be alowed,</l>
                  <l>That ſetteth light his promiſe to forget.</l>
                  <l>And for my part, I wyl not linke in loue,</l>
                  <l>With fickle folke, whoſe fancies oft remoue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My happy gaine, I doo eſteeme for ſuch,</l>
                  <l>As fewe haue found, in theſe our doutful dayes:</l>
                  <l>To finde a freend, I thinke it be as much,</l>
                  <l>Aſte winne, a fort full fraught of noble praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Of all the goodes, that there may be poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>A faithfull freend, I iudge to be the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O freendly league, although to late begunne,</l>
                  <l>Yet time ſhall try our troth, is well imployed:</l>
                  <l>And that we both ſhall ſee, that we haue wonne,</l>
                  <l>Such faſtned faith, as can not be deſtroyed.</l>
                  <l>By enuious rage, or ſlaunders bitter blowe</l>
                  <l>That ſeekes the good, to ouerthrowe,</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> No woordes, but deedes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE wrong is great, the paine aboue my power,</l>
                  <l>That yeeldes ſuch care in doutfull dennes to drowne:</l>
                  <l>Such happe is hard, where fortune dooth ſo lower,</l>
                  <l>As freendly looke, is turned to froward frowne.</l>
                  <l>Is this the truſt that faithfull treendes can finde?</l>
                  <l>With thoſe that yet haue promiſe broke?</l>
                  <l>By deedes in dout, as though no woordes can binde,</l>
                  <l>A vowed freend to hold him to his yoke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O faithleſſe freend? what can aſſure your minde,</l>
                  <l>That doutes ſo ſoone, before you haue cauſe why?</l>
                  <l>To what hard happe? dooth Fortune here me binde,</l>
                  <l>When woordes nor deedes can no way ſatiſfye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5735:10"/>What can I write? that hath not oft been
ſaide?</l>
                  <l>What haue I ſaide? that other hath not affyrmed?</l>
                  <l>What is approued? that ought to be aſſayed?</l>
                  <l>Or what is vowed? that ſhall not be performed?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Caſt of miſtruſt, in haſte no credite giue,</l>
                  <l>To this or that, that breedeth freendes vnreſt:</l>
                  <l>No doubt at all, but truſt me if I liue,</l>
                  <l>My deedes ſhall prooue, that all is for the beſt.</l>
                  <l>And this beleeue, the Sea ſhall ceaſſe to flowe,</l>
                  <l>The Sunne to ſhine within the ſetled ſkie:</l>
                  <l>All thinges on earth, ſhall leaue to ſpring and growe,</l>
                  <l>Yea euery foule ſhall want, his winges to flye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eare I in thought, ſhall ſeeme once to retyre,</l>
                  <l>If you my freend remaine, as I deſyre:</l>
                  <l>Nowe loſe no time, but vſe that whyle you may,</l>
                  <l>Forget not this, a dogge ſhall haue a day.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> He deſyreth exchange of lyfe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE day delayed, of that I moſt doo wiſhe,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith I feede and ſtarue, in one degree:</l>
                  <l>With wiſhe and want, ſtill ſerued in one diſhe,</l>
                  <l>Aliue as dead, by proofe as you may ſowe.</l>
                  <l>To whom of olde, this prouerbe well it ſerues,</l>
                  <l>Whyle graſſe dooth growe, the ſeelly Horſe he
ſterues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tweene theſe extreames, thus doo I rome the race,</l>
                  <l>Of my poore life, this certaynely I knowe:</l>
                  <l>Tweene would and want, vnwarely that dooth paſſe,</l>
                  <l>More ſwift then ſhot, out of the archers howe.</l>
                  <l>As Spider drawes her line in vayne all day,</l>
                  <l>I watch the net, and others haue the pray,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5735:10"/>
                  <l>And as by proofe, the greedy dogge d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>The bared bone, all onely for the taſte:</l>
                  <l>So to and fro, this lothſome life I drawe,</l>
                  <l>With fancies forſt, and fled with vaine repaſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narſiſſus</hi> brought vnto the water brinke,</l>
                  <l>So aye thirſt I, the more that I doo drinke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe thus I dye, and yet I ſeeme not ſicke,</l>
                  <l>With ſmart vnſeene, my ſelfe my ſelfe I weare:</l>
                  <l>With prone deſire, and power that is not quicke,</l>
                  <l>With hope aloft nowe drenched in diſpaire,</l>
                  <l>Trayned in truſt, for no reward aſſignd,</l>
                  <l>The more I haſte, the more I come behinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With hurt to heale, in frozen yſe to frye,</l>
                  <l>With loſſe to laugh, this is a woonderous caſe:</l>
                  <l>Faſt fetred here, is forſte away to flye,</l>
                  <l>As hunted Hare, that Hound hath in the chaſe.</l>
                  <l>With winges and ſpurres, for all the haſte I make,</l>
                  <l>As like to loſe, as for to drawe the ſtake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The dayes be long, that hang vpon deſert,</l>
                  <l>The life is irke of ioyes that be delayed:</l>
                  <l>The time is ſhort, for to requite the ſmart,</l>
                  <l>That dooth proceede of promiſe long vnpaid,</l>
                  <l>That to the laſt of this my fainting breath,</l>
                  <l>I wiſhe exchange of life, for happy death.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Of the instabilitie of youth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHEN I looke backe, and in my ſelfe beholde,</l>
                  <l>The wandring wayes, that youth could not deſcry:</l>
                  <l>And markt the fearefull courſe that youth did holde,</l>
                  <l>And mette in mind, eache ſteppe youth ſtrayed a wry.</l>
                  <l>My knees I bowe, and from my hart I call,</l>
                  <l>O Lorde, forget theſe faultes and follies all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5735:11"/>
                  <l>For nowe I ſee, howe voyde youth is of ſkill,</l>
                  <l>I ſee alſo his prime time and his end:</l>
                  <l>I doo confeſſe my faultes and all my yll,</l>
                  <l>And ſorrowe ſore, for that I did offend.</l>
                  <l>And with a mind repentant of all crimes,</l>
                  <l>Pardon I aſke for youth, ten thouſand times.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The humble hart, hath daunted the proud mind,</l>
                  <l>Eke wyſedome hath geuen ignorance a fall:</l>
                  <l>And wit hath taught, that folly could not finde,</l>
                  <l>And age hath youth, her ſubiect and her thrall.</l>
                  <l>Therefore I pray, O Lorde of life and trueth,</l>
                  <l>Pardon the faultes committed in my youth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that dydſt graunt the wyſe king his requeſt?</l>
                  <l>Thou that in Whale, thy prophet didſt preſerue:</l>
                  <l>Thou that forgaueſt the wounding of thy breſt?</l>
                  <l>Thou that dydſt ſaue the theefe in ſtate to
ſterue.</l>
                  <l>Thou only God, the geuer of all grace?</l>
                  <l>Wipe out of mind, the path of youthes vaine race.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that by power, to lyfe didſt rayſe the dead.</l>
                  <l>Thou that of grace reſtoreſt the blinde to ſight:</l>
                  <l>Thou that for loue, thy life and loue out bled,</l>
                  <l>Thou that of fauour, madeſt the lame goe ryght.</l>
                  <l>Thou that canſt heale, and helpe in all aſſayes,</l>
                  <l>Forgeue the gilth, that grewe in youthes vayne wayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And nowe ſince I, with faith and doubtleſſe minde,</l>
                  <l>Doo fly to thee by prayer, to appeaſe thy yre:</l>
                  <l>And ſince that thee, I onely ſeeke to finde,</l>
                  <l>And hope by faith, to attayne my iuſt deſyre.</l>
                  <l>Lorde, minde no more youthes error and vnſkill,</l>
                  <l>And able age, to doo thy holy wyll.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. Vaux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="subpart">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5735:11"/>
               <head>14.
<l>Most happy is that state alone,</l>
                  <l>Where woordes and deedes agree in one.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BY painted woordes, the ſilly ſimple man,</l>
                  <l>To truſtleſſe trappe, is trayned now and than.</l>
                  <l>And by conſeyte, of ſweete alluring tale,</l>
                  <l>He bites the baites, that breedes his bitter bale.</l>
                  <l>To beawties blaſt, caſt not thy rolling eye:</l>
                  <l>In pleaſaunt greene, doo ſtinging Serpent lye.</l>
                  <l>The golden Pill, hath but a bitter taſte:</l>
                  <l>In glittering glaſſe, a poyſon ranckeſt plaſte.</l>
                  <l>So pleaſant woordes, without perfourming deedes:</l>
                  <l>May well be deemed, to ſpring of Darnel ſeedes.</l>
                  <l>The freendly deede is it, that quickly tryes:</l>
                  <l>Where truſty faith, and freendly meaning lyes.</l>
                  <l>That ſtate therefore, moſt happy is to me:</l>
                  <l>Where woordes and deedes, moſt faithfully agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My freend, yf thou wylt keepe thy honeſt name:</l>
                  <l>Fly from the blotte, of barking ſlaunders blame.</l>
                  <l>Let not in woord, thy promiſe be more large:</l>
                  <l>Then thou in deede, art wylling to diſcharge.</l>
                  <l>Abhorred is that falſe diſſembling broode,</l>
                  <l>That ſeemes to beare, two faces in one hoode.</l>
                  <l>To ſay a thing, and not to meane the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Wyll turne at length, to loſe of thy good name.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore my freend, let double dealing goe:</l>
                  <l>In ſteade whereof, let perfect plaineneſſe flowe.</l>
                  <l>Doo thou no more, in idle woordes exceede:</l>
                  <l>Then thou intendes to doo, in very deede.</l>
                  <l>So good report, ſhall ſpreade thy woorthy prayſe:</l>
                  <l>For being iuſt in woord and deede alwayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You worldly wightes, that worldly dooers are:</l>
                  <l>Before you let your woord ſlip foorth to farre,</l>
                  <l>Conſyder wel, what inconuenience ſpringes:</l>
                  <l>By breache of promiſe made, in lawfull thinges.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:5735:12"/>Firſt, God miſlikes where ſuch
deceite dooth ſwarme:</l>
                  <l>Next, it redoundeth vnto thy neighbours harme.</l>
                  <l>And laſt of all, which is not leaſt of all:</l>
                  <l>For ſuch offence, thy conſcience ſuffer ſhall.</l>
                  <l>As barren groundes, bringes foorth but rotten weedes:</l>
                  <l>From barren woordes, ſo fruiteleſſe chaffe
proceedes.</l>
                  <l>As ſauerie flowres, doo ſpring in fertill ground:</l>
                  <l>So truſty freendes, by tryed freendes are found.</l>
                  <l>To ſhunne therefore the woorſt, that may enſue:</l>
                  <l>Let deèdes alway, approue thy ſayinges true.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="subpart">
               <head>15.
<l>Who wyll aſpire to dignitie,</l>
                  <l>By learnyng must aduaunced be.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE poore that liue in needie rate,</l>
                  <l>By learning doo great richeſſe gayne:</l>
                  <l>The riche that liue in wealthy ſtate,</l>
                  <l>By learnyng doo their wealth mainteyne.</l>
                  <l>Thus ritch and poore, are furthered ſtill.</l>
                  <l>By ſacred rules of learned ſkill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All fond conceites of franticke youth.</l>
                  <l>The golden gyft of learning ſtayes:</l>
                  <l>Of doubtfull thinges to ſearche the trueth,</l>
                  <l>Learning ſets foorth the reddy wayes.</l>
                  <l>O happy him doo I repute,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe breſt is fraught with learninges fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There growes no Corne within the feelde.</l>
                  <l>That Oxe and Plough did neuer tyll:</l>
                  <l>Right ſo the mind no fruite can yeelde.</l>
                  <l>That is not lead by learninges ſkill.</l>
                  <l>Of ignoraunce comes rotten weedees,</l>
                  <l>Of learnyng ſpringes right noble deedes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5735:12"/>
                  <l>Like as the Captayne hath reſpect.</l>
                  <l>To trayne his ſouldiers in aray:</l>
                  <l>So Learning dooth mans mind direct.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Vertues</hi> ſtaffe his lyfe to ſtay.</l>
                  <l>Though Freendes and Fortune waxeth ſkant.</l>
                  <l>Yet learned men ſhall neuer want.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You Impes therefore in youth be ſure.</l>
                  <l>To fraught your mindes with learned thinges:</l>
                  <l>For Learning is the fountayne pure,</l>
                  <l>Out from the which all glory ſpringes.</l>
                  <l>Who ſo therefore wyll glory winne,</l>
                  <l>With Learning fyrſt, muſt needes beginne.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="subpart">
               <head>16.
<l>Mans flitting life, fyndes ſurest stay,</l>
                  <l>Where ſacred Vertue beareth ſway.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE ſturdy Rocke, for all his ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>By raaging Seas, is rent in twayne:</l>
                  <l>The Marble ſtone, is pearſt at length,</l>
                  <l>With little droppes, of driſlyng rayne.</l>
                  <l>The Oxe dooth yeelde vnto the yoke,</l>
                  <l>The Steele obeyeth the hammer ſtroke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſtately Stagge, that ſeemes ſo ſtout,</l>
                  <l>By yalpyng Houndes, at bay is ſet:</l>
                  <l>The ſwifteſt Bird, that flees about,</l>
                  <l>Is caught at length in Fowlers net.</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Fiſhe in deepeſt Brooke,</l>
                  <l>Is ſoone deceiued with ſubtil hooke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ye man him ſelfe, vnto whoſe wyll,</l>
                  <l>All thinges are bounden to obay:</l>
                  <l>For all his witte, and woorthy ſkill,</l>
                  <l>Dooth fade at length, and fall away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5735:13"/>There is nothing, but time dooth
waſt,</l>
                  <l>The Heauens, the Earth, conſume at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Vertue</hi> ſittes, triumphing ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Trone, of glorious <hi>Fame:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though ſpitefull Death, mans body kill,</l>
                  <l>Yet hurtes he not, his vertuous name.</l>
                  <l>By Life or death, what ſo be tides,</l>
                  <l>The ſtate of <hi>Vertue,</hi> neuer ſlides.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Nothing is comparable vnto a faithfull
freend.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SIth this our time of Freendſhip is ſo ſcant,</l>
                  <l>Sith Freendſhip nowe in euery place dooth want.</l>
                  <l>Sith euery man of Freendſhip is ſo hollowe,</l>
                  <l>As no man rightly knowes which way to followe.</l>
                  <l>Seaſe not my Muſe, ceaſe not in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>To ryng loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If men be nowe, their owne peculier freendes,</l>
                  <l>And to their neighbours Freendſhip none pretendes.</l>
                  <l>If men of Freendſhip ſhewe them ſelues ſo bare,</l>
                  <l>And of their brethren take no freendly care.</l>
                  <l>Forbeare not then my Muſe, nor feare not then,</l>
                  <l>To ryng diſprayſe of theſe vnfreendly men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did man of Freendſhip knowe the mightie power?</l>
                  <l>Howe great effectes it woorketh euery houre.</l>
                  <l>What ſtore of hidden freendſhip it retaynes,</l>
                  <l>How ſtill it powreth foorth aboundaunt gaynes.</l>
                  <l>Man would with thee my muſe in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Ryng out loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Freendſhip, releeueth mans neceſſitie,</l>
                  <l>Freendſhip, comforteth mans aduerſitie.</l>
                  <l>Freendſhip augmenteth mans proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>Frendſhip preferres man to felicitie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5735:13"/>Then ryng my muſe, ryng out in theſe
our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Ring out loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of Freendſhip, groweth loue and charitie,</l>
                  <l>By Freendſhip, men are linked in amitie:</l>
                  <l>From Freendſhip, ſpringeth all commoditie,</l>
                  <l>The fruite of Freendſhip, is fidelitie.</l>
                  <l>Oh ryng my Muſe, ryng out in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Peale vpon peale, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That man with man, true Freendſhip may embrace,</l>
                  <l>That man to man, may ſhewe a freendly face:</l>
                  <l>That euery man, may ſowe ſuch freendly ſeedes,</l>
                  <l>As Freendſhip, may be found in freendly deedes.</l>
                  <l>And ioyne with me my Muſe in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>To ryng loude peales, of ſacred Freendſhips prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="subpart">
               <head>18. Reſpiſe finem.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO be as wyſe as <hi>CATO</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>Or ritch as <hi>CRESVS</hi> in his life:</l>
                  <l>To haue the ſtrength of <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whiche did ſubdue by force or ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>What helpeth it when Death doth call,</l>
                  <l>The happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Ritche may well the Poore releeue,</l>
                  <l>The Rulers may redreſſe eche wrong:</l>
                  <l>The Learned may good counſell geue,</l>
                  <l>But marke the ende, of this my ſong.</l>
                  <l>Who dooth theſe thinges, happy they call,</l>
                  <l>Their happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The happieſt end, in theſe our dayes,</l>
                  <l>That all doo ſeeke, both ſmall and great:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5735:14"/>Is eyther for Fame, or els for
Prayſe,</l>
                  <l>Or who may ſltte in higheſt ſeate.</l>
                  <l>But of theſe thinges, hap what hap ſhall,</l>
                  <l>The happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A good beginning oft we ſee,</l>
                  <l>But ſeeldome ſtandyng at one ſtay:</l>
                  <l>For fewe doo lyke the meme degree,</l>
                  <l>Then prayſe at parting ſome men ſay.</l>
                  <l>The thing whereto eache wight is thrall,</l>
                  <l>The happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The meane eſtate, that happy life,</l>
                  <l>Whiche liueth vnder gouernaunce:</l>
                  <l>Who ſeekes no hate nor breedes no ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>But takes in woorth his happy chaunce,</l>
                  <l>If contentation him befall,</l>
                  <l>His happy end, exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The longer lyfe that we deſyre,</l>
                  <l>The more offence dooth dayly growe:</l>
                  <l>The greater paine it dooth require.</l>
                  <l>Except the Iudge ſome mercie ſhewe.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I thinke, and euer ſhall,</l>
                  <l>The happy ende exceedeth all.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> He perſwadeth his freend, from the fond
effectes of loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHY art thou bound, and maiſt goe free,</l>
                  <l>Shall reaſon yeelde to raging wyll?</l>
                  <l>Is thraldome like to libertie:</l>
                  <l>Wylt thou exchange thy good for ill:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhalt thou learne a childiſhe play,</l>
                  <l>And of eche part to taſte and proue,</l>
                  <l>The lookers on, ſhall iudge and ſay,</l>
                  <l>Loe this is he that liues by loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5735:14"/>
                  <l>Thy wittes with thoughtes, ſhal ſtand at ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Thy head ſhall haue but heauie reſt:</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes ſhall watche for wanton prayes,</l>
                  <l>Thy tongue ſhall ſhewe thy hartes requeſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy eares ſhall heare a thouſand noyſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy hand ſhall put thy pen to paine:</l>
                  <l>And in the ende, thou ſhalt diſpraiſe,</l>
                  <l>The life ſo ſpent, for ſuch ſmall gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If leue and liſt might neuer cope,</l>
                  <l>Nor youth to runne from reaſons race:</l>
                  <l>Nor yf ſtrong ſute might winne ſure hope,</l>
                  <l>I would leſſe blame a louers caſe.</l>
                  <l>For loue is hotte, with great deſire,</l>
                  <l>And ſweete delight makes youth ſo fond,</l>
                  <l>That little ſparkes wyl prooue great fyre,</l>
                  <l>And bring free hartes to endleſſe bond.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Wantyng his deſyre, be complayneth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſayling ſhips with ioy at lenght, do touche the long
deſired port,</l>
                  <l>The hewing axe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oke doth waſte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battring Canon
breakes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fort.</l>
                  <l>Hard hagard Haukes ſtope to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lure, wild co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
bridle tames,</l>
                  <l>There is nothing ſo out of vre, but to his kinde long time
it frames.</l>
                  <l>Yet this I finde in time, no time can winne my ſute,</l>
                  <l>Though oft the tree I clime, I can not catche the fruite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet the pleaſant branches oft, in yeelding wyſe to me
doo bowe,</l>
                  <l>When I would touch, they ſpring aloft, ſone are they gone,
I wot not howe:</l>
                  <l>Thus I purſue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleting flood, like <hi>Tantalus</hi> in
hel belowe.</l>
                  <l>Would god my caſe ſhe vnderſtood, which can ful ſone
releue my woe:</l>
                  <l>Which yf to her were knowen, the fruite were ſurely
mine,</l>
                  <l>She would not let me grone, and brouſe vpon the rine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But if my ſhip with tackle turne, with rented ſailes
muſt needes retire,</l>
                  <l>And ſtreame &amp; wind had plainely ſworne, by force to
hinder my deſire:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5735:15"/>Like one that ſtrikes vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rocks, my
weerie wrack I ſhould bewaſte</l>
                  <l>And learne to know falſe fortunes mocks, who ſmiles on me
to ſmall auaile:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſith ſhe only can, my rented ſhip reſtore,</l>
                  <l>To helpe her wracked man, but once I ſeeke no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Trye before you trust.</head>
               <l>IN freendes are found a heape of doubtes, that double dealing
vſe,</l>
               <l>A ſwarme of ſuch I could finde out, whoſe craft I can
accuſe:</l>
               <l>A face for loue, a hart for hate, theſe faigned freendes can
beare,</l>
               <l>A tongue for troth, a head for wyles, to hurt eche ſimple
eare.</l>
               <l>In humble port is poyſon pact, that plaineneſſe can not
ſpie,</l>
               <l>Which credites all, and can not ſee, where ſtinging
ſerpentes lye:</l>
               <l>Through haſtie truſt, the harmeleſſe hart, is eaſely
hampred in,</l>
               <l>And made beleeue it is good golde, when it is lead and tin.</l>
               <l>The firſt deceit that bleares mine eyes, is faigned faith
profeſt,</l>
               <l>The ſecond trappe, is grating talke, that gripes eche
ſtrangers breſt,</l>
               <l>The third deceit, is greeting woordes, with colours painted
out,</l>
               <l>Which biddes ſuſpect to feare no ſmart, nor dread no
dangerous dout.</l>
               <l>The fourth and laſt, is long repaire, which creepes in
freendſhips lap:</l>
               <l>And dayly hauntes, that vnder truſt, deuiſeth many a
trap.</l>
               <l>Lo how falſe freendes, can frame a fetch, to winne the wil
with wyles,</l>
               <l>To ſauce their ſleightes with ſugred ſops, &amp;
ſhadowe harme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſmiles.</l>
               <l>To ſerue their luſtes, are ſundry ſortes, by practiſe
diuers kindes,</l>
               <l>Some carries honnie in their mouthes, and venime in their
mindes.</l>
               <l>Mee thinkes the ſtones within the ſtreetes, ſhould crie
out in this caſe,</l>
               <l>And euery one that doth them meete, ſhould ſhunne their
double face.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> A Lady forſaken, complayneth.</head>
               <l>IF pleaſures be in painefulneſſe? in pleaſures dooth my
body reſt,</l>
               <l>If ioyes accorde with carefulneſſe? a ioyfull hart is in my
breſt:</l>
               <l>If priſon ſtrong be libertie? in libertie long haue I
been,</l>
               <l>If ioyes accord with miſerie? who can compare a lyfe to
myne.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5735:15"/>Who can vnbind that is ſore bound? who can
make free y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſore thrall</l>
               <l>Or how can any meanes be found? to comfort ſuch a wretch
withall?</l>
               <l>None can, but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath my hart, conuert my paines to comfort
then,</l>
               <l>Yet ſince his ſeruant I became, moſt like a bondman haue I
beene:</l>
               <l>Since firſt in bondage I became, my woord and deede was euer
ſuch,</l>
               <l>That neuer once he could me blame, except from louing him too
much.</l>
               <l>Which I can iudge no iuſt offence, nor cauſe that I
deſerud diſdayne,</l>
               <l>Except he meane through falſe prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, through forged loued
to make a traine</l>
               <l>Nay nay alas, my fained thoughts my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded &amp; my fained
ruth</l>
               <l>My pleaſures paſt my preſent plaints, ſhew wel I meane
but to much truth:</l>
               <l>But ſince I can not him attaine, againſt my wil I let him
goe,</l>
               <l>And leſt he glorie at my paine, I wyl attempt to cloke my
woe.</l>
               <l>Youth, learne by me, but doo not proue, for I haue proued to my
paine,</l>
               <l>What greeuous greefes do grow by loue, &amp; what it is to loue
in vaine.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="subpart">
               <head>23. Finding worldly ioyes but vanities, he wyſheth
death.</head>
               <l>FOrlorne in filthy froward fate, wherein a thouſand cares I
finde,</l>
               <l>By whom I doo lament my ſtate, annoide with fond afflicted
mind:</l>
               <l>A wretche in woe, and dare not crie,</l>
               <l>I liue, and yet I wiſhe to dye.</l>
               <l>The day in dole, that ſeemeth long, I pas with ſighes &amp;
heauy cheere,</l>
               <l>And with theſe eyes I vewe the wrong, that I ſuſtaine by
louing here:</l>
               <l>Where my miſhappes as rife doo dwell,</l>
               <l>As plagues within the pit of hell.</l>
               <l>A wailing wight I walke alone, in deſart dennes there to
complaine,</l>
               <l>Among the ſauage ſort to mone, I flee my frends where they
remaine:</l>
               <l>And pleaſure take to ſhun the ſight,</l>
               <l>Where erſt I felt my cheefe delight.</l>
               <l>A captiue clapt in chaynes of care, lapt in the lawes of lethall
loue,</l>
               <l>My fleſhe &amp; bones conſumed bare, with crauling greefes
ful ſtrange to proue:</l>
               <l>Though hap dooth bidde me hope at leaſt,</l>
               <l>Whiles graſſe dooth growe, yet ſtarues the beaſt.</l>
               <l>A ſeeged fort with forraine force, for want of ayde, muſt
yeelde at laſt,</l>
               <l>So muſt my weeried pined corſe, ſubmit it ſelfe to
bitter taſt:</l>
               <l>Of crauling care, that carkes my breſt,</l>
               <l>Tyll hop or death, ſhall breede my reſt.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="subpart">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5735:16"/>
               <head>24.
<l>Hauing marryed a woorthy Lady,</l>
                  <l>and taken away by death, he complayneth his
miſhap.</l>
               </head>
               <l>IN youth when I at large did leade, my life in luſtie
libertie,</l>
               <l>When heuy thoughtes no one did ſpreade, to let my pleaſant
fanteſie</l>
               <l>No fortune ſeemd, ſo hard could fall,</l>
               <l>This freedome then, that might make thrall.</l>
               <l>And twentie yeres I ſkarſe had ſpent, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make ful my
happy fate,</l>
               <l>Both treaſures great were on me caſt, with landes and titles
of eſtate:</l>
               <l>So as more bleſt then I ſtoode than,</l>
               <l>Eke as me thought was neuer man.</l>
               <l>For of Dame Fortune who is he, coulde more deſyre by iuſt
requeſt,</l>
               <l>The health, with wealth, and libertie, al which at once I thus
poſſeſt:</l>
               <l>But maſkyng in this ioly ioy,</l>
               <l>A ſoden ſyght, prooud al a toy.</l>
               <l>For paſſyng on theſe merie dayes, with new deuice of
pleaſures great,</l>
               <l>And now &amp; then to viewe the rayes, of beauties workes with
cunnyng fret:</l>
               <l>In heauenly hewes, al which as one,</l>
               <l>I oft behelde, but bounde to none.</l>
               <l>And one day rowlyng thus my eyes, vpon theſe bleſſed
wyghts at eaſe,</l>
               <l>Among the reſt one dyd I ſee, who ſtrayght my wandryng
lookes dyd ſeaſe:</l>
               <l>And ſtayed them firme, but ſuche a ſyght,</l>
               <l>Of beautie yet ſawe neuer wyght.</l>
               <l>What ſhal I ſeke to praiſe it more, where tongs can not
praiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame,</l>
               <l>But to be ſhort to louers lore, I ſtrayght my ſenſes al
dyd frame:</l>
               <l>And were it wyt, or were it chaunce,</l>
               <l>I woonne the Garlande in this daunce,</l>
               <l>And thus wher I before had thought, no hap my fortune might
encreſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>A double blis this chance forth brought, ſo did my ladies loue
me pleſe:</l>
               <l>Her fayth ſo firme, and conſtant ſuche,</l>
               <l>As neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hart, can prayſe too muche.</l>
               <l>But now with torments ſtrange I taſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fickle ſtay of
fortunes whele,</l>
               <l>And where ſhe rayſde from height to caſt, with greater
force, of greefe to feele:</l>
               <l>For from this hap of ſoden frowne,</l>
               <l>Of Princes face ſhe threwe me downe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5735:16"/>And thus exchange now hath it made, my
libertie a thing moſt deare,</l>
               <l>In hateful priſon for to fade, where ſundred from my louing
feare:</l>
               <l>My wealth, and health, ſtandes at like ſtay,</l>
               <l>Obſcurely to conſume away.</l>
               <l>And laſt when humaine force was none, could part our loue
wherin we liued,</l>
               <l>My ladyes life alas is gone, moſt cruel death hath it
bereued:</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertues, her, to God, hath wonne,</l>
               <l>And leaſt me here, a man vndone.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. G.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="subpart">
               <head>24.
<l>A woorthy dittie, ſong before the Queenes</l>
                  <l>Maiestie at Bristowe.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MIſtruſt not troth, that truely meanes, for euery ielous
freke,</l>
                  <l>In ſteade of wrong, condemne not right, no hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrath to
wreke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Looke on the light of faultleſſe life, how bright her
vertues ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And meaſure out her ſteppes eche one, by leuel and by
line.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deeme eche deſert by vpright geſſe, whereby your
prayſe ſhal liue,</l>
                  <l>If malice would be match with might, let hate no iudgement
geue:</l>
                  <l>Enforſe no feare with wreſting wittes, in quiet
conſcience breſt,</l>
                  <l>Lend not your eares to buſie tongues, which breedeth much
vnreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In doubtfull driftes wade not to farre, it weeries but the
mind,</l>
                  <l>Seeke not to ſearch the ſecret harts, whoſe thoughtes
are hard to find:</l>
                  <l>Auoide from you thoſe hatefull heads, that helpes to heape
miſhapp,</l>
                  <l>Be flowe to heare the flatterers voyce, which creepeth in your
lapp.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Embrace their loue that wills you good, and ſport not at
their praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Truſt not too much vnto your ſelfe, for feeble are your
ſtaies:</l>
                  <l>Howe can your ſeate be ſetled faſt, or ſtand on
ſtedfaſt ground,</l>
                  <l>So propped vp with hollowe hartes, whoſe ſuertie is
vnſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Geue faith to thoſe that feare for loue, and not that loue
for feare,</l>
                  <l>Regard not them that force compels, to pleaſe you euery
where:</l>
                  <l>All this well waide and borne away, ſhall ſtabliſhe long
your ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Continually with perfect peace, in ſpite of puffing
hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="subpart">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5735:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> His good name being blemiſhed, he
bewayleth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRaud is the front of Fortune paſt all recouerie,</l>
                  <l>I ſtayles ſtand, to abide the ſhocke of ſhame and
infamie.</l>
                  <l>My life through lingring long is lodge, in lare of lothſome
wayes,</l>
                  <l>My death delaide to keepe from life, the harme of hapleſſe
dayes:</l>
                  <l>My ſprites, my hart, my witte and force, in deepe
diſtreſſe are dround,</l>
                  <l>The only loſſe of my good name, is of theſe greefes the
ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince my mind, my wit, my head, my voyce, and tongue are
weake</l>
                  <l>To vtter, mooue, deuiſe, conceiue, ſound foorth, declare,
and ſpeake:</l>
                  <l>Such pearſing plaintes, as anſweare might, or would my
wofull caſe,</l>
                  <l>Helpe, craue I muſt, and craue I wyll, with teares vpon my
face:</l>
                  <l>Of al that may in heauen or hell, in earth or ayre be
found,</l>
                  <l>To wayle with me this loſſe of mine, as of theſe greefes
the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Helpe gods, helpe ſaintes, helpe ſprites &amp; powers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
in the heauen doo dwel,</l>
                  <l>Helpe ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are to wayle aye woont, ye howling hounds of
hel:</l>
                  <l>Helpe man, helpe beaſts, helpe birds, &amp; wormes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth doth toile</l>
                  <l>Helpe fiſhe, helpe foule, that flocks and feedes vpon the
ſalt ſea ſoyle:</l>
                  <l>Helpe eccho that in ayre dooth flee, ſhryl voyces to
reſound,</l>
                  <l>To wayle this loſſe of my good name, as of theſe greefes
the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Of Fortunes power.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>POlicrates</hi> whoſe paſſing happe, cauſd him to
loſe his fate,</l>
                  <l>A golden ryng caſt in the ſeas, to change his conſtant
ſtate,</l>
                  <l>And in a fiſhe yet at his bourd, the fame he after
found,</l>
                  <l>Thus Fortune loe, to whom ſhe takes, for bountie dooth
abound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The myzers vnto might ſhe mountes, a common caſe we
ſee,</l>
                  <l>And mightie in great miſerie, ſhe ſets in lowe
degree:</l>
                  <l>Whom ſhe to day dooth reare on hie, vpon her whitling
wheele,</l>
                  <l>To morowe next ſhedingeth downe, and caſteth at her
heele.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5735:17"/>
                  <l>No meaſure hath ſhee in her gifts, ſhee doth reward
eache ſort.</l>
                  <l>The wiſe that counſell haue, no more then fooles that
maketh ſport.</l>
                  <l>Shee vſeth neuer partiall handes for to offend or
pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Geue me good Fortune all men ſayes, and throw me in the
ſeas.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is no fault or worthines, that makes men fall or
riſe,</l>
                  <l>I rather be borne Fortunate, then to be very wiſe.</l>
                  <l>The blindeſt man right ſoone, that by good Fortune guided
is,</l>
                  <l>To whome that pleaſant Fortune pipes, can neuer daunce
amis.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="subpart">
               <head>28.
<l>Though Triumph after bloudy warres, the greatest brags do
beare:</l>
                  <l>Yet Triumph of a conquered minde, the crowne of Fame shall
weare.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo ſo doth marke the careleſſe life, of theſe
vnhappie dayes,</l>
                  <l>And ſees what ſmall and ſlender hold, the ſtate of
vertue ſtayes:</l>
                  <l>He findes that this accurſed trade, proceedeth of this
ill,</l>
                  <l>That men be giuen, too much to yeelde to their vntamed
will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In lacke of taming witleſſe wil, the poore we often
ſee</l>
                  <l>Enuies the ritch, becauſe that he, his equall cannot
bee:</l>
                  <l>The rich aduauned to might by wealth, from wrong doth not
refraine,</l>
                  <l>But will oppreſſeth weaker ſort, to heape exceſſiue
gaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If Fortune were ſo blinde, to geue to one man what he
will,</l>
                  <l>A world would not ſuffiſe the ſame, if he might haue his
fill:</l>
                  <l>We wiſh, we ſearche, we ſtriue for all, and haue no more
therin</l>
                  <l>Then hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaue, when death doth come, though
<hi>Creſus</hi> welth we win.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In getting much, we get but care, ſuch brittle wealth to
keepe,</l>
                  <l>The rich within his walles of ſtone doth neuer ſoundly
ſleepe:</l>
                  <l>When poore in weake and ſlender houſe, doe feare no
loſſe of wealth,</l>
                  <l>And haue no further care but this, to keepe them ſelues in
health.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Affection may not hide the ſword of ſway, in iudgement
ſeat,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt partiall law doe execute the lawe in cauſes
great:</l>
                  <l>But if the minde in conſtant ſtate, affection quite doe
leaue,</l>
                  <l>The higher ſtate ſhall haue their rights, the poore no
wrong receaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5735:18"/>
                  <l>It is accompted greater praiſe to <hi>Ceaſars</hi> loftie
ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Againſt his vanquiſt foes, in warres to bridle wrekefull
hate:</l>
                  <l>Then when to <hi>Rome</hi> he had ſubdued, the people long
vnknowne,</l>
                  <l>Wherby as farre as land was found, the ſame abrode was
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If honor can ſelfe will refuſe, and iuſtice be
vpright,</l>
                  <l>And priuate ſtate deſires but that which good appeares in
ſight:</l>
                  <l>Then vertue ſhall with ſoueraigne ſhow, to euery eye
reueale</l>
                  <l>A heauenly life, a wealefull ſtate, a happie common
weale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let vertue then the Triumph win, and gouerne all your
deedes,</l>
                  <l>Your yeelding to er ſober heaſtes, immortall glory
breede:</l>
                  <l>Shee ſhall vpreare your worthy name, ſhew then vnto the
ſkies,</l>
                  <l>Her beames ſhall ſhine in graue obſcure, where ſhrined
carkeſſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>29</hi> Of perfect wiſedome.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo ſo will be accompted wiſe, and truely claime the
ſame,</l>
                  <l>By ioyning vertue to his deedes, he muſt atchieue the
ſame:</l>
                  <l>But fewe there be, that ſeeke thereby true wiſedome to
attaine,</l>
                  <l>O God, ſo rule our hearts therefore, ſuch fondneſſe to
refraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wiſedome which we moſte eſteeme, in this thing doth
conſiſt,</l>
                  <l>With glorious talke to ſhew in wordes our wiſedome when we
liſt.</l>
                  <l>Yet not in talke, but ſeemely deedes, our wiſedome we
ſhould place,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake ſo faire, and doe but ill, doth wiſedome quite
diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To bargaine well, and ſhunne the loſſe, a wiſedome
counted is,</l>
                  <l>And thereby through the greedie coyne no hope of grace to
mis.</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke by honoure to aduaunce his name to brittle
praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Is wiſedome, which we da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly ſee, increaſeth in our
dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But heauenly wiſedome ſower ſeemes to hard for them to
win,</l>
                  <l>And weary of the ſute they ſeeme, when they doe once
begin:</l>
                  <l>It teacheth vs to frame our life, while vitall breth we
haue,</l>
                  <l>When it diſſolueth earthly maſſe, the ſoule from
death to ſaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5735:18"/>
                  <l>By feare of God to rule our ſteppes, from ſliding into
vice,</l>
                  <l>A wiſedome is, which we neglect, although of greater
price:</l>
                  <l>A poynt of wiſedome alſo this, we commonly eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>That euery man ſhould be in deede, that he deſires to
ſeeme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To bridle that deſire of gaine, which forceth vs to ill,</l>
                  <l>Our hawtie ſtomackes Lord repreſſe, to tame preſuming
will:</l>
                  <l>This is the wiſedome that we ſhould, aboue eache thing
deſire,</l>
                  <l>O heauenly God from ſacred throne, that grace in vs
inſpire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And print in our repugnant hearts, the rules of wiſedome
true,</l>
                  <l>That all our deedes in worldly life, may like thereof
inſue:</l>
                  <l>Thou onely art the liuing ſpring, from whome this wiſedome
flowes,</l>
                  <l>O waſhe therewith our ſinfull heartes, from vice that
therin growes.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>30</hi> A frendly admonition.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YE ſtately wightes, that liue in quiet reſt</l>
                  <l>Through worldly wealth, which God hath giuen to you.</l>
                  <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment with teares and ſighes from dolefull breſt:</l>
                  <l>The ſhame and power that vice obtaineth now.</l>
                  <l>Behold how God doth daily profer grace,</l>
                  <l>Yet we diſdaine, repentance to embrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſuddes of ſinne doe ſucke into the mind,</l>
                  <l>And cancred vice doth vertue quite expell,</l>
                  <l>No chaunge to good alaſſe can reſting finde:</l>
                  <l>Our wicked hearts ſo ſtoutly doe rebell.</l>
                  <l>Not one there is that haſteth to amend,</l>
                  <l>Though God from heauen his daily threates doe ſend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We are ſo ſlow to chaunge our blamefull life,</l>
                  <l>We are ſo preſt to ſnatche aluring vice:</l>
                  <l>Such greedie hartes on euery ſide be rife.</l>
                  <l>So few that guide their will by counſell wiſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſet our teares lament the wretched caſe,</l>
                  <l>And call to God for vndeſerued grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5735:19"/>
                  <l>You worldly wightes, that haue your fancies ſixt</l>
                  <l>On ſlipper ioy of terreine pleaſure here:</l>
                  <l>Let ſome remorſe in all your deedes be mixt.</l>
                  <l>Whiles you haue time let ſome redreſſe appere.</l>
                  <l>Of ſodaine Death the houre you ſhall not know,</l>
                  <l>And looke for Death atthough it ſeemeth ſlow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh be no iudge in other mens offence,</l>
                  <l>But purge thy ſelfe and ſeeke to make thee free,</l>
                  <l>Let euery one applie his diligence,</l>
                  <l>A chaunge to good with in him ſelfe to ſee:</l>
                  <l>O God direct our feete in ſuch a ſtay,</l>
                  <l>From cancred vice to ſhame the hatefull way.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>31.</hi> Sundrie men, ſundrie affectes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN euery wight ſome ſondrie ſort of pleaſure I doe
finde,</l>
                  <l>Which after he doth ſeeke to eaſe his toyling minde.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi> with her training chaſe, of hunting had
delight,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the fearefull Deare, ſhee could direct her
ſhotte aright.</l>
                  <l>The loftie yeares in euery age, doth ſtill imbrace the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame,</l>
                  <l>The ſport is good, if vertue doe aſſiſt the chearefull
game.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerua</hi> in her chattering armes her courage doth
aduaunce,</l>
                  <l>In triall of the bloudie warres, ſhee giueth luckie
chaunce.</l>
                  <l>For ſauegard men imbrace the ſame, which doe ſo
needefull ſeeme,</l>
                  <l>That noble heartes their cheefe delights in vſe therof
eſteeme.</l>
                  <l>In warlike games to ride or trie the force of armes they
vſe,</l>
                  <l>And baſe the man we doe accompt, that doth the ſame
refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſiluer ſound of muſickes cordes, doth pleaſe
<hi>Apollos</hi> wit,</l>
                  <l>A ſcience which the heauens aduaunce, where it deſerues to
ſit.</l>
                  <l>A pleaſure apt for euery wight, releefe to carefull
minde,</l>
                  <l>For woe redreſſe, for care a ſalue, for ſadneſſe
helpe we finde.</l>
                  <l>The ſoueraigne praiſe of Muſicke ſtill, doth cauſe
the Poetes faine,</l>
                  <l>That whliring Spheres, and eke the heauens, do hecmonie
retaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5735:19"/>
                  <l>I heard that theſe three powers, at variaunce lately
fell,</l>
                  <l>Whiles eache did praiſe his owne delight, the other to
excell.</l>
                  <l>Then Fame, as one indifferent iudge, to ende the caſe they
call,</l>
                  <l>The praiſe pronounced by her to them, indifferently doth
fall.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi> health and ſtrength maintaine,
<hi>Minerua</hi> force doth tame,</l>
                  <l>And Muſicke geues ſweete delight, to further other
game.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe three delightes to hawtie mindes, the worthieſt are
eſtemed,</l>
                  <l>If vertue be anexed to them, they rightly be ſo demed.</l>
                  <l>With ioy they doe releeue the witte with ſorrow oft
oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And neuer ſuffer ſolempne greefe too long in minde to
reſt.</l>
                  <l>Be wiſe in mirth, and ſeeke delight, the ſame doe not
abuſe,</l>
                  <l>In honeſt mirth, a happie ioy we ought not to refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Time giues experience.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WE reade what paines the powers deuine,</l>
                  <l>Through wrath conceiued by ſome offence,</l>
                  <l>To mortall creatures they aſſigne</l>
                  <l>Their due deſartes for recompence.</l>
                  <l>What endleſſe paine they muſt endure,</l>
                  <l>Which their offences did procure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Gripe doth <hi>Titius</hi> Liuer teare</l>
                  <l>His greedie hungrie gorge to fill,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sisiphus</hi> muſt euer beare</l>
                  <l>The rowling ſtone againſt the hill.</l>
                  <l>A number moe in hell be found,</l>
                  <l>Which thus to endleſſe paine are bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet all the woe that they ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Is nothing to the paine of me,</l>
                  <l>Which cometh through the proude diſdaine</l>
                  <l>Of one, that doth to loue repine:</l>
                  <l>Therefore I crie woe worth the houre,</l>
                  <l>Since firſt I fell in <hi>Venus</hi> power.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5735:20"/>
                  <l>The gnawing gripes of irkſome thought,</l>
                  <l>Conſumes my heart with <hi>Titius</hi> griefe:</l>
                  <l>I alſo haue full vainly wrought,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Sisiphus</hi> without reliefe.</l>
                  <l>Euen when I hope to ende my paine,</l>
                  <l>I muſt renue my ſute againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet will I not ſeeme ſo vntrue,</l>
                  <l>To leaue a thing ſo late begone:</l>
                  <l>A better happe may yet inſue,</l>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt towres in time be wonne.</l>
                  <l>In time therefore, my truſt I place,</l>
                  <l>Who muſt procure deſired grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>33</hi> Of ſufferance cometh eaſe.</head>
               <l>TO ſeeme for to reuenge eache wrong in haſtie wiſe,</l>
               <l>By proofe we ſee of guiltleſſe men, it hath not bene th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
guiſe.</l>
               <l>In ſlaunders lothſome brute, where they condemned bee,</l>
               <l>With rageleſſe moode they ſuffer wrong, where truth ſhal
trie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> free.</l>
               <l>Theſe are the patient panges, that paſſe within the
breſt</l>
               <l>Of thoſe, that feele their cauſe by mine, where wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hath
right oppreſt.</l>
               <l>I know how by ſuſpect, I haue bene iudgd awrie,</l>
               <l>And graunted g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltie in the thing, that cleerely I denie:</l>
               <l>My faith may me defend, if I might loued be,</l>
               <l>God iudge me ſo, as from the guilt I know me to be free.</l>
               <l>I wrote but for my ſelfe, the griefe was all mine owne,</l>
               <l>As, who would proue excremitie, by proofe it might be
knowne.</l>
               <l>Yet are there ſuche, that ſay, they can my meaning
deeme,</l>
               <l>Without reſpect of this olde trothe, things proue not as they
ſeeme,</l>
               <l>Whereby it may befall, in iudgement to be quicke,</l>
               <l>To make them ſelues ſuſpect therewith, that needed not to
kicke.</l>
               <l>Yet in reſiſting wrong, I would not haue it thought</l>
               <l>I do amiſſe, as though I knew by whome it might be
wrought.</l>
               <l>If any ſuche there be, that heerewithall be vext,</l>
               <l>It were their vertue to beware, and deeme me better next.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="subpart">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5735:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>34</hi> Being trapped in Loue be complayneth.</head>
               <l>THe hidden wees that ſwelleth in my hart,</l>
               <l>Brings forth ſuche ſighes, as filles the aire with
ſmoke:</l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e golden beames, thorow this his fierie dart,</l>
               <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not abide, the anſwere of the ſtroke.</l>
               <l>Which ſtroke, although it dazed me ſome dele,</l>
               <l>Yet nature taught my hand to worke his kinde,</l>
               <l>Wherewith I taught to pull away the ſtele,</l>
               <l>But to my paine, it left my head behinde,</l>
               <l>That faſtned hath my heart ſo neare the pith,</l>
               <l>Except ſuche ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lue, as when the Scorpion ſtinges,</l>
               <l>I might rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue to heale my wounde therewith:</l>
               <l>In vaine for eaſe, my tongue alwayes it ringes.</l>
               <l>And I for paines, ſhall peariſh through her guilt,</l>
               <l>That can reioyce, to ſee how I am ſpilt.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="subpart">
               <head>35
<l>Though Fortune haue ſette thee on hie,</l>
                  <l>Remember yet that thou ſhalt die.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO die, Dame nature did man frame,</l>
                  <l>Death is a thing moſt perfect ſure:</l>
                  <l>We ought not natures workes to blame,</l>
                  <l>Shee made nothing, ſtill to endure.</l>
                  <l>That lawe ſhee made, when we were borne,</l>
                  <l>That hence we ſhould retourne againe:</l>
                  <l>To render right, we muſt not ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Death is due debt, it is no paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ciuill lawe, doth bidde reſtore</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt taken vp of truſt:</l>
                  <l>Thy life is lent, thou muſt therfore</l>
                  <l>Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, except thou be vniuſt.</l>
                  <l>This life is like a poynted race,</l>
                  <l>To the ende wherof when man hath trode,</l>
                  <l>He muſt returne to former place,</l>
                  <l>He may not ſtill remaine abrode.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5735:21"/>
                  <l>Death hath in all the earth aright,</l>
                  <l>His power is great, it ſtretcheth farre:</l>
                  <l>No Lord, no Prince, can ſcape his might,</l>
                  <l>No creature can his duetie barre.</l>
                  <l>The wiſe, the iuſt, the ſtrong, the hie,</l>
                  <l>The chaſt, the meeke, the free of hart,</l>
                  <l>The rich, the poore, who can denie,</l>
                  <l>Haue yeelded all vnto his dart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could <hi>Hercules</hi> that tamde eache wight?</l>
                  <l>Or elſe <hi>Vliſses</hi> with his witte?</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Ianus</hi> who had all foreſight?</l>
                  <l>Or chaſt <hi>Hypolit</hi> ſcape the pitte?</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Creſus</hi> with his bagges of golde?</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Irus</hi> with his hungrie paine?</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Signus</hi> through his hardineſſe bolde?</l>
                  <l>Driue backe the dayes of Death againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Seeing no man then can Death eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Nor hire him hence for any gaine:</l>
                  <l>We ought not feare his carraine ſhape,</l>
                  <l>He onely brings euell men to paine.</l>
                  <l>If thou haue ledde thy life aright,</l>
                  <l>Death is the ende of miſerie:</l>
                  <l>If thou in God haſt thy delight,</l>
                  <l>Thou dieſt to liue eternallie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eache wight therefore while he liues heere,</l>
                  <l>Let him thinke on his dying day:</l>
                  <l>In midſt of wealth, in midſt of cheere,</l>
                  <l>Let him accompt he muſt away.</l>
                  <l>This thought, makes man to God a frend,</l>
                  <l>This thought doth baniſh pride and ſinne:</l>
                  <l>This thought doth bring a man in thend,</l>
                  <l>Where he of Death the field ſhall win.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="subpart">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:5735:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>39</hi> All thinges ar Vaine.</head>
               <l>ALthough the purple morning, bragges in brightnes of the
ſunne,</l>
               <l>As though he had of chaſed night, a glorious conqueſt
wonne:</l>
               <l>The Time by day, giues place againe to forſe of drowſie
night,</l>
               <l>And euery creature is conſtraind, to chaunge his luſtie
plight.</l>
               <l>Of pleaſures all, that heere we taſte:</l>
               <l>We feele the contrary at laſte.</l>
               <l>In ſpring, though pleaſant <hi>Zephirus,</hi> hath frutefull
earth inſpired,</l>
               <l>And nature hath each buſhe, each branch, with bloſſomes
braue attired:</l>
               <l>Yet fruites and flowers, as buds and blomes, full quickly
witherd be,</l>
               <l>When ſtormie Winter comes to kill, the Somers iolitie.</l>
               <l>By Time are gotte, by Time are loſt</l>
               <l>All things, wherein we pleaſure moſt.</l>
               <l>Although the Seas ſo calmely glide, as daungers none
appeare,</l>
               <l>And dout of ſtormes, in ſkie is none, king <hi>Phebus</hi>
ſhines ſo cleare:</l>
               <l>Yet when the boiſtrous windes breake out, and raging waues do
ſwel,</l>
               <l>The ſeely barke now heaues to heauen, now ſinkes againe to
hel.</l>
               <l>Thus chaunge in euery thing we ſee,</l>
               <l>And nothing conſtant, ſeemes to bee.</l>
               <l>Who floweth moſt in worldly wealth, of wealth is moſt
vnſure,</l>
               <l>And he that cheefely taſtes of ioy, doth ſometime woe
indure:</l>
               <l>Who vaunteth moſt of numbred frends, forgoe them all he
muſt,</l>
               <l>The faireſt fleſh and liueleſt bioud, is turnd at length
to duſt.</l>
               <l>Experience geues a certaine grounde,</l>
               <l>That certen heere, is nothing founde.</l>
               <l>Then truſt to that which aye remaines, the bliſſe of
heauens aboue,</l>
               <l>Which Time, nor Fate, nor Winde, nor Storme, is able to
remoue:</l>
               <l>Truſt to that ſure celeſtiall rocke, that reſtes in
glorious throne,</l>
               <l>That hath bene, is, and muſt be ſtill, our anker holde
alone.</l>
               <l>The world is but a vanitie,</l>
               <l>In heauen ſeeke we our ſuretie.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>37</hi> A vertuous Gentle woman in the praiſe of his
Loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am a Virgine faire and free, and freely doe
reioyce,</l>
                  <l>I ſweetely warble ſugred notes, from ſiluer voyce:</l>
                  <l>For which delightfull ioyes, yet thanke I curteſie loue,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe allmightie power, ſuch ſweete delites I
proue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5735:22"/>
                  <l>I walke the pleaſant fieldes, adornd with liuely greene,</l>
                  <l>And view the fragrant flowres, moſt louely to be
ſeene:</l>
                  <l>The purple Columbine, the Couſloppe and the Lillie,</l>
                  <l>The Violet ſweete, the Daizie and Daffadillie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Woodbines on the hedge, the red Roſe and the white,</l>
                  <l>And cache fine flowres elſe, that rendreth ſweete
delite:</l>
                  <l>Among the which I chooſe, all thoſe of ſeemelieſt
grace,</l>
                  <l>In thought, reſembling them to my deare louers face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His louely face I meane, whoſe golden flouring giftes,</l>
                  <l>His euer liuing Fame, to loftie ſkie vpliftes:</l>
                  <l>Whom louing me I loue, onely for vertues ſake,</l>
                  <l>When vertuouſly to loue, all onely care I take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of all which freſhe faire flowers, that flowre that doth
appeare</l>
                  <l>In my conceit moſt like to him I holde ſo deare.</l>
                  <l>I gather it, I kiſſe it, and eake deuiſe with it,</l>
                  <l>Suche kinde of liuely ſpeeche, as is for louers fit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And then of all my flowres, I make a garland fine,</l>
                  <l>With which my golden wyer heares, together I doe twine:</l>
                  <l>And ſette it on my head, ſo taking that delight,</l>
                  <l>That I would take, had I my louer ſtill in ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For as in goodly flowres, myne eyes great pleaſure
finde,</l>
                  <l>So are my louers gyftss, moſt pleaſant to my minde:</l>
                  <l>Vpon which vertuous gyftes, I make more ſweete repaſt,</l>
                  <l>Then they that for loue ſportes, the ſweeteſt ioyes doo
taſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Oppreſſed with ſorowe, he wyſheth
death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF Fortune may enforce, the carefull hart to cry,</l>
                  <l>And griping greefe conſtrayne, the wounded wight lament:</l>
                  <l>Who then alas to mourne, hath greater cauſe then I,</l>
                  <l>Agaynſt whoſe hard miſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p, both Heauen and Earth are
bent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5735:22"/>For whom no helpe remaynes, for whom no
hope is left:</l>
                  <l>From whom all happy happes is fled, and pleaſure quite
bereft.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe lyfe nought can prolong, whoſe health nought can
aſſure:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe death, oh pleaſant port of peace, no creature can
procure.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe paſſed proofe of pleaſant ioy,</l>
                  <l>Miſchaunce hath chaunged, to greefes anoy:</l>
                  <l>And loe, whoſe hope of better day,</l>
                  <l>Is ouerwhelmd with long delay.</l>
                  <l>Oh hard miſhap.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Eache thing I plainely ſee, whoſe vertues may auayle,</l>
                  <l>To eaſe the pinching payne, which gripes the groning
wyght:</l>
                  <l>By Phiſickes ſacred ſkill, whoſe rule dooth ſeldome
fayle,</l>
                  <l>Through labours long inſpect, is playnely brought to
lyght.</l>
                  <l>I knowe, there is no fruite, no leafe, no roote, no rynde,</l>
                  <l>No hearbe, no plant, no iuyce, no gumme, no mettal deepely
mind:</l>
                  <l>No Pearle, no Precious ſtone, ne Ieme of rare effect,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues, learned <hi>Gallens</hi> bookes, at lardge
doo not detect.</l>
                  <l>Yet all theyr force can not appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>The furious fyttes of my diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor any drugge of Phiſickes art,</l>
                  <l>Can eaſe the greefe, that gripes my hart.</l>
                  <l>Oh ſtraunge diſeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I heare the wyſe affyrme, that Nature hath in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand ſecrete ſalues, which Wyſdome hath
outfound:</l>
                  <l>To coole the ſcorching heate of euery ſmarting ſore:</l>
                  <l>And healeth deepeſt ſcarre, though greeuous be the
wound.</l>
                  <l>The auncient prouerbe ſayes, that none ſo feſtred
greefe,</l>
                  <l>Dooth grow, for which the gods them ſelues, haue not ordeynd
releefe.</l>
                  <l>But I by proofe doo knowe, ſuch prouerbes to be vayne,</l>
                  <l>And thinke that Nature neuer knewe, the plague which I
ſuſtayne.</l>
                  <l>And ſo not knowyng my diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Hath leaft my greefe remedileſſe,</l>
                  <l>For why, the heauens for me prepare,</l>
                  <l>To liue in thought, and dye in care.</l>
                  <l>Oh laſtyng payne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By chaunge of ayre I ſee, by haute of healthfull
ſoyle,</l>
                  <l>By dyet duely kept, groſe humours are expeld:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5735:23"/>I know that greefes of minde, and inward
heartes turmoile,</l>
                  <l>By faithfull frendes aduiſe, in time may be repeld.</l>
                  <l>Yet all this nought auailes, to kill that me anoyes,</l>
                  <l>I meane to ſtoppe theſe floudes of care, that ouerflow my
ioyes.</l>
                  <l>No none exchaunge of place, can chaunge my luckleſſe
lot,</l>
                  <l>Like one I liue, and ſo muſt die, whome Fortune hath
forgoe.</l>
                  <l>No counſell can preuaile with mee,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſage aduiſe with greefe agree:</l>
                  <l>For he that feeles the paines of hell,</l>
                  <l>Can neuer hope in heauen to dwell.</l>
                  <l>Oh deepe deſpaire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What liues on earth but I, whoſe trauaile reapes no
gaine,</l>
                  <l>The wearyed Horſe and Oxe, in ſtall and ſtable
reſt:</l>
                  <l>The Ante with ſommers toyle, beares out the winters
paine,</l>
                  <l>The Fowle that flies all day, at night retournes to
reſt.</l>
                  <l>The Ploughmans weary worke, amid the winters mire,</l>
                  <l>Rewarded is with ſomers gaine, which yeeldes him double
hire:</l>
                  <l>The ſillye laboring ſoule, which drudges from day to
day,</l>
                  <l>At night, his wages truely paide, contented goth his way.</l>
                  <l>And comming home, his drowſie hed</l>
                  <l>He cowcheth cloſe in homely bed:</l>
                  <l>Wherein no ſooner downe he lies,</l>
                  <l>But ſleepe hath ſtraight poſſeſt his eyes.</l>
                  <l>Oh happie man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Souldier biding long, the brunt of mortall warres,</l>
                  <l>Where life is neuer free, from dint of deadly foyle:</l>
                  <l>At laſt comes ioyfull home, though mangled all with
ſcarres,</l>
                  <l>Where frankly, voyde of feare, he ſpendes the gotten
ſpoyle.</l>
                  <l>The Pirate lying long, amidde the fooming floodes,</l>
                  <l>With euery flawe in hazard is, to looſe both life and
goodes.</l>
                  <l>At length findes view of land, where wiſhed Porte he
ſpies,</l>
                  <l>Which once obtained, among his mates, he partes the gotten
priſe.</l>
                  <l>Thus euery man, for trauaile paſt,</l>
                  <l>Doth reape a iuſt reward at laſt:</l>
                  <l>But I alone, whoſe troubled minde,</l>
                  <l>In ſeeking reſt, vnreſt doth finde.</l>
                  <l>Oh luckleſſe lotte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5735:23"/>
                  <l>Oh curſſed caitife wretche, whoſe heauie harde
miſhappe,</l>
                  <l>Doth wiſh tenne thouſande times, that thou hadſt not
bene borne:</l>
                  <l>Since fate hathe thee condemned, to liue in ſorrowes
lappe.</l>
                  <l>Where waylinges waſte thy life, of all redreſſe
forlorne.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall thy griefe appeaſe? who ſhall thy torment
ſtay?</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou thy ſelfe, with murthering handes, enforce thy
owne decay?</l>
                  <l>No, farre be thou from me, my ſelfe to ſtoppe my
breath,</l>
                  <l>The gods forbid, whom I beſeeche, to worke my ioyes by
death.</l>
                  <l>For lingering length of lothed life,</l>
                  <l>Doth ſtirre in mee ſuch mortall ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>That whiles for life and death I crie,</l>
                  <l>In Death I liue, and liuing die.</l>
                  <l>Oh froward fate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe heere my hard miſhappe, loe heere my ſtraunge
diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Loe heere my deepe deſpaire, loe heere my laſting
paine:</l>
                  <l>Loe heere my froward fate, which nothing can appeaſe.</l>
                  <l>Loe heere how others toyle, rewarded is with gaine.</l>
                  <l>While luckeleſſe, loe, I liue in loſſe of laboures
due,</l>
                  <l>Compeld by proofe of torment ſtrong, my endleſſe greefe
to rue.</l>
                  <l>In which, ſince needes I muſt, conſume both youth and
age</l>
                  <l>If olde I liue, and that my care no comfort can
aſſwage.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth I baniſhe from my breſt,</l>
                  <l>All fruſtrate hope of future reſt,</l>
                  <l>And truthleſſe truſt to times reward,</l>
                  <l>With all reſpectes of ioyes regard,</l>
                  <l>Here I forſweare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="subpart">
               <head>39
<l>Where reaſon makes request, there wiſedome ought
ſupplie,</l>
                  <l>With friendly anſwere prest, to graunt or elſe
denie.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Sigh? why ſo? for ſorrowe of her ſmart.</l>
                  <l>I morne? wherfore? for greefe that ſhee complaines.</l>
                  <l>I pitie? what? her ouerpreſſed hart.</l>
                  <l>I dread? what harme? the daunger ſhee ſuſtaines,</l>
                  <l>I greeue? where at? at her oppreſſing paines.</l>
                  <l>I feele? what forſe? the fittes of her diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe harme doth me and her, alike diſpleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5735:24"/>
                  <l>I hope, what happe? her happy healthes retyre,</l>
                  <l>I wiſhe, what wealth? no wealth, nor worldly ſtore</l>
                  <l>But craue, what craft? by cunnyng to aſpyre</l>
                  <l>Some ſkyll, whereto? to ſalue her ſickly ſore.</l>
                  <l>What then? why then would I her health reſtore,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe harme me hurtes, howe ſo? ſo woorkes my wyll</l>
                  <l>To wyſhe my ſelfe and her, lyke good and yll.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What moues the mind, whereto? to ſuch deſyre</l>
                  <l>Ne force, ne fauour, what then? free fancies choyſe:</l>
                  <l>Art thou to chooſe? my charter to require</l>
                  <l>Eache Ladyes loue is fred by cuſtomes voyce,</l>
                  <l>Yet are there grauntes, the euidence of theyr choyſe.</l>
                  <l>What then, our freedome is at lardge in chooſyng,</l>
                  <l>As womens willes are froward in refuſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wotes ſhe thy wyll? ſhe knowes what I proteſt,</l>
                  <l>Daynde ſhe thy ſute? ſhe daungerd not my talke:</l>
                  <l>Gaue ſhe conſent? ſhe graunted my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>What dydſt thou craue? the roote, the fruite, or
ſtalke,</l>
                  <l>I aſked them all, what gaue ſhe, Cheeſe, or chalke?</l>
                  <l>That taſte muſt try, what taſte? I meane the proofe</l>
                  <l>Of freendes, whoſe wyls withhold her bowe aloofe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Meanſt thou good fayth? what els, hopeſt thou to
ſpeede?</l>
                  <l>Why not, O foole vntaught in carpet trade,</l>
                  <l>Knoweſt not what proofes from ſuch delayes proceede,</l>
                  <l>Wylt thou like headles Cocke be caught in glade?</l>
                  <l>Art thou like Aſſe, too apt for burden made?</l>
                  <l>Fy, fy, wyl thou for ſaint adore the ſhrine?</l>
                  <l>And woo her freend, eare ſhe be wholy thine?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who drawes this drift? moued ſhe, or thou this match?</l>
                  <l>Twas I: oh foole, vnware of womens wyles,</l>
                  <l>Long mayſt thou wayte, like hungry houndes at hatche,</l>
                  <l>She crafty Foxe, the ſeely Gooſe beguiles.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5735:24"/>Thy ſute is ſhaped ſo fyt for long
delay,</l>
                  <l>That ſhee at wyll may chek, from yea to nay,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But in good ſoothe, tell me her frendes intent:</l>
                  <l>Beſt learne it firſt, their purpoſe I not knowe,</l>
                  <l>Why then thy will to woorſe and worſe is bent,</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou delight, the vnkindled cole to blowe?</l>
                  <l>Or childelike loueſt, in anckred bote to rowe,</l>
                  <l>What meane theſe termes? who ſith thy ſute is
ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Know of or on, or thou afect to much.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No haſte but good, why no, the meane is beſt,</l>
                  <l>Admit ſhee loue, miſlike in lingring growes:</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe ſhee is caught, then Woodcocke on thy creſt,</l>
                  <l>Till end approues, what ſkornefull ſedes ſhee
ſowes.</l>
                  <l>In loytring loue, ſuch dangers ebbes and flowes,</l>
                  <l>What helpe herein? why wake in dangerous watch,</l>
                  <l>That too, nor fro, may make thee marre the match:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is that the way to ende my wery woorke?</l>
                  <l>By quicke diſpatch, to leſſon long turmoyle,</l>
                  <l>Well well, though loſſe in lingering wontes to lurke,</l>
                  <l>And I a foole, moſt fitte to take the foyle:</l>
                  <l>Yet proofe from promiſe, neuer ſhall recoyle.</l>
                  <l>My woordes with deedes, and deedes with woordes ſhal
wend,</l>
                  <l>Tyll ſhee, or hers, gayueſay that I entend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Art thou ſo fond? not fond, but firmely faſt,</l>
                  <l>Why foole, her freendes wote how thy wyl is bent:</l>
                  <l>Yet thou lyke doult, whoſe witte and ſenſe is
paſt,</l>
                  <l>Seſt not what frumpes, doo folowe thy entent.</l>
                  <l>Ne knowe, how loue in lewe of ſkorne is lent,</l>
                  <l>Adewe, for ſightes ſuch folly ſhould preuent.</l>
                  <l>Well well, their ſkoffes with ſcornes might be repaid,</l>
                  <l>If my requeſtes were fully yead or nayd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5735:25"/>
                  <l>Well, well, let theſe with wiſedomes paſſe be
waide,</l>
                  <l>And in your cheſt of cheefeſt ſecreates laide.</l>
                  <l>What is, or may be mine,</l>
                  <l>That is, and ſhall be thine:</l>
                  <l>Till death the twiſt vntwine,</l>
                  <l>That doth our loues combine.</l>
                  <l>But if thy heart repine,</l>
                  <l>Thy body ſhould be mine.</l>
                  <l>Shew me thereof ſome ſine,</l>
                  <l>That I may ſlacke the line,</l>
                  <l>That knitts thy will to mine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis. My Lucke is loſſe.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="subpart">
               <head>40
<l>Donec eris Felix multos numerabis amicos.</l>
                  <l>Nullus ad amiſsus ibit amicus opes.</l>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as the Rauen, the Crowe, and greedie Rite</l>
                  <l>Doe ſwarming flocke, where carren corpes doth fall:</l>
                  <l>And tiring teare with beake and talentes might,</l>
                  <l>Both ſkin and fleſhe to gorge their guttes withall.</l>
                  <l>And neuer ceaſe, but gather moe to moe,</l>
                  <l>Doe all to pull the carkaſe too and froe,</l>
                  <l>Till bared bones at laſt they leaue behinde,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeke elſewhere, ſome fatter foode to finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Euen ſo I ſee, where wealth doth waxe at will,</l>
                  <l>And Golde doth growe to heapes of great encreaſe:</l>
                  <l>There frendes reſort, and profering frendſhip ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Full thicke they throng, with neuer ceaſing preaſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſtilie make a ſhew of true intent,</l>
                  <l>When nought but guile, and inwarde hate is ment:</l>
                  <l>For when miſchaunce ſhall chaunge ſuch wealth to
want,</l>
                  <l>They packe them thence, to place of ritcher haunt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis. My Lucke is loſſe.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="subpart">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5735:25"/>
               <head>41. What ioye to a contented mynde.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe faithe that failes, muſt nedes be thought vntrue,</l>
                  <l>The frende that faines, who holdeth not vniuſt,</l>
                  <l>Who likes that loue, that chaungeth ſtill for newe:</l>
                  <l>Who hopes for truthe, where trothe is voide of truſt,</l>
                  <l>No faithe, no frende, no loue, no trothe ſo ſure,</l>
                  <l>But rather failes then ſtedfaſtly endure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What head ſo ſtaied? that altereth not intent,</l>
                  <l>What thought ſo ſure? that ſtedfaſt doeth remaine,</l>
                  <l>What witte ſo wiſe? that neuer nedes repent:</l>
                  <l>What tonge ſo true? but ſometyme wonts to faine,</l>
                  <l>What foote ſo firme? that neuer treads awrie,</l>
                  <l>What ſoner dimde? then fight of clereſt eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What harte ſo fixt? but ſome enclines to change,</l>
                  <l>What moode ſo milde? that neuer moued debate:</l>
                  <l>What faithe ſo ſtrong? but lightly likes to range,</l>
                  <l>What loue ſo true? that neuer learnde to hate.</l>
                  <l>What life ſo pure? that laſts, without offence,</l>
                  <l>What worldly mynde? but moues with ill pretence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What knot ſo faſt? that maie not be vntide,</l>
                  <l>What ſeale ſo ſure? but fraude or forſe ſhall
breke:</l>
                  <l>What prop of ſtaye? but one tyme ſhrinks aſide,</l>
                  <l>What ſhip ſo ſtauche? that neuer had a leke.</l>
                  <l>What graunt ſo large? that no exception maks,</l>
                  <l>What hoped helpe? but frende at nede forſaks.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſeate ſo high? but lowe to grounde maie fall,</l>
                  <l>What hap ſo good? that neuer founde miſlike:</l>
                  <l>What ſtate ſo ſure? but ſubiect is to thrall</l>
                  <l>What force preuailes? where Fortune liſte to ſtrike.</l>
                  <l>What wealth ſo muche? but tyme maie turne to want,</l>
                  <l>What ſtore ſo greate? but waſtyng maketh ſkant.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:5735:26"/>
                  <l>What profites hope in depth of dangers thrall,</l>
                  <l>What ruſte in tyme, but waxeth worſe and worſe:</l>
                  <l>What helpes good harte, if Fortune froune withall,</l>
                  <l>What bleſſyng thriues, gainſt heauenly helples
curſe.</l>
                  <l>What winnes deſire, to get and can not gaine,</l>
                  <l>What botes to wiſhe and neuer to obtaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis. My lucke is loſſe.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="subpart">
               <head>42. Amantium irae amoris redintigratia eſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN goyng to my naked bedde, as one that would haue
ſlept,</l>
                  <l>I heard a wife ſyng to her child, that long before had
wept:</l>
                  <l>She ſighed ſore and ſang full ſore, to bryng the babe
to reſt,</l>
                  <l>That would not reſt but cried ſtill, in ſuckyng at her
breſt.</l>
                  <l>She was full wearie of her watche, and greued with her
child,</l>
                  <l>She rocked it and rated it, vntill on her it ſmilde:</l>
                  <l>Then did ſhe ſaie now haue I founde, the prouerbe true to
proue,</l>
                  <l>The fallyng out of faithfull frends, is the renuyng of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then tooke I paper, penne and ynke, this prouerbe for to
write,</l>
                  <l>In regeſter for to remaine, of ſuche a worthie wight:</l>
                  <l>As ſhe proceded thus, in ſong vnto her little bratte,</l>
                  <l>Muche matter vttered ſhe of waight, in place whereas ſhe
ſatte.</l>
                  <l>And proued plaine, there was no beaſt, nor creature bearyng
life,</l>
                  <l>Could well be knowne to liue in loue, without diſcorde and
ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>Then kiſſed ſhe her little babe, and ſware by God
aboue,</l>
                  <l>The fallyng out of faithfull frends, is the renuyng of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She ſaied that neither kyng ne prince, ne lorde could liue
aright,</l>
                  <l>Vntill their puiſſance thei did proue, their manhode &amp;
their might</l>
                  <l>When manhode ſhalbe matched ſo, that feare can take no
place,</l>
                  <l>Then wearie works makes warriours, eche other to embrace.</l>
                  <l>And leaue their forſe that failed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche did conſume
the rout,</l>
                  <l>That might before haue liued their tyme, and nature out:</l>
                  <l>Then did ſhe ſyng as one that thought, no man could her
reproue,</l>
                  <l>The fallyng out of faithfull frendes, is the renuyng of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:5735:26"/>
                  <l>She ſaied ſhe ſawe no fiſhe ne foule, nor beaſt
within her haunt,</l>
                  <l>That mete a ſtraunger in their kinde, but could geue it a
taunt:</l>
                  <l>Since fleſhe might not indure, but reſte muſt wrathe
ſuccede,</l>
                  <l>And forſe the fight to fall to plaie, in paſture where
thei feede.</l>
                  <l>So noble nature can well ende, the works ſhe hath
begone,</l>
                  <l>And bridle well that will not ceaſe, her tragedy in
ſome:</l>
                  <l>Thus in her ſonge ſhe oft reherſt, as did her well
behoue,</l>
                  <l>The fallyng out of faithfull frends, is the renuyng of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I meruaile muche pardy quoth ſhe, for to beholde the
route,</l>
                  <l>To ſee man, woman, boy &amp; beaſt to toſſe the worlde
about:</l>
                  <l>Some knele, ſome crouch, ſome beck, ſome check, &amp;
ſome ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſmothly ſmile</l>
                  <l>And ſome embrace others in armes, and there thinke many a
wile.</l>
                  <l>Some ſtande aloufe at cap and knee, ſome humble and ſome
ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Yet are thei neuer frends indeede, vntill thei once fall
out:</l>
                  <l>Thus ended ſhe her ſong, and ſaied before ſhe did
remoue,</l>
                  <l>The fallyng out of faithfull frends, is the renuyng of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwardes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="subpart">
               <head>43. Thinke to dye.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe life is long, whiche lothſomely doeth laſte,</l>
                  <l>The dolfull daies drawe ſlowly to their date:</l>
                  <l>The preſent panges, and painfull plags forepaſt,</l>
                  <l>Yelds greffe aye grene, to ſtabliſhe this eſtate.</l>
                  <l>So that I feele in this greate ſtorme and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>That death is ſweete, that ſhorteneth ſuche a life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And by the ſtroke of this ſtraunge ouerthrowe,</l>
                  <l>All whiche conflict in thraldome I was thruſt:</l>
                  <l>The Lorde be praiſed, I am well taught to knowe,</l>
                  <l>From whens man came, and eke whereto he muſt.</l>
                  <l>And by the waie, vpon how feble force,</l>
                  <l>His terme doeth ſtande, till death doeth ende his
courſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pleaſant yeres that ſemes ſo ſwetely ronne,</l>
                  <l>The mery daies to ende, ſo faſt that flete:</l>
                  <l>The ioyfull wights, of whiche daies dawes ſo ſone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:5735:27"/>The happie howrs, whiche mo doe miſſe
then mete.</l>
                  <l>Doe all conſume as ſnowe againſt the Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And death maks ende of all that life begonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since death ſhall dure till all the worlde be waſt,</l>
                  <l>What meaneth man, to dread death then ſo ſore?</l>
                  <l>As man might make, that life ſhould alwaie laſt,</l>
                  <l>Without regard, the Lorde hath ledde before.</l>
                  <l>The daunce of death, whiche all muſt runne on rowe,</l>
                  <l>The hower wherein onely hymſelf doeth knowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If man would mynde, what burdeins life doeth bryng,</l>
                  <l>What greuous crimes to God, he doeth commit:</l>
                  <l>What plagues, what panges, what perill thereby ſpryng,</l>
                  <l>With no ſure hower in all his daies to ſit.</l>
                  <l>He would ſure thinke and with greate cauſe I doo,</l>
                  <l>The daie of death is happier of the twoo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death is the doore whereby we drawe to ioye,</l>
                  <l>Life is a lake, that drowneth all in paine:</l>
                  <l>Death is ſo dole it ſeaſeth all awaie,</l>
                  <l>Life is ſo leude that all it yelds is vaine.</l>
                  <l>And as by life, in bondage man is brought.</l>
                  <l>Euen ſo by death is freedome likewiſe wrought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherefore with Paule, let all men wiſhe and praie,</l>
                  <l>To be diſolued of this foule fleſhly maſſe:</l>
                  <l>Or at the leaſt be armed againſt the daie,</l>
                  <l>That thei be founde good ſouldiers preſt to paſſe.</l>
                  <l>From life to death, from death to life againe,</l>
                  <l>And ſuche a life as euer ſhall remaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>D. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="subpart">
               <head>44. Beyng aſked the occaſion of his white head, he
aunſwereth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHere ſethyng ſighes and ſower ſobbs,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſlaine the ſlipps that nature ſett:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:5735:27"/>And ſkaldyng ſhowers with ſtonie
throbbs,</l>
                  <l>The kindly ſappe from them hath fett.</l>
                  <l>What wonder then though you doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where thought hath thrild and throne his ſpeares,</l>
                  <l>To hurt the harte that harmth hym not:</l>
                  <l>And gronyng grief hath grounde for the teares,</l>
                  <l>Myne eyne, to ſtaine my face to ſpot.</l>
                  <l>What wonder then though you doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where pinchyng paine hym ſelf hath plaſte,</l>
                  <l>There peace with pleaſures were poſſeſt:</l>
                  <l>And walles of wealth are fallen to waſte,</l>
                  <l>And pouertie in them is preſt.</l>
                  <l>What wonder then, though you doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where wretched woe doeth weaue her webbe,</l>
                  <l>There care the clewe, can catche and caſte:</l>
                  <l>And floudds of ioye are fallen to ebbe</l>
                  <l>So loe, that life maie not long laſte.</l>
                  <l>What wonder then, though you doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head white heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe heeres of age are meſſengers,</l>
                  <l>Whiche bidd me, faſt repent and praie:</l>
                  <l>Thei be of death the harbingers,</l>
                  <l>That doeth prepare, and dreſſe the waie.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I ioye, that you maie ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuche heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thei be the line that lead the length,</l>
                  <l>How farre my race was for to ronne:</l>
                  <l>Thei ſaie my yongth is fledde with ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>And how old age, is well begonne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5735:28"/>The whiche I feele, and you maie ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuche lines to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thei be the ſtryngs of ſober ſounde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Muſicke is hermonicall:</l>
                  <l>Their tunes declare, a tyme from grounde</l>
                  <l>I came, and how thereto I ſhall.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I ioye that you maie ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuche ſtryngs to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God graunt to thoſe that white heeres haue,</l>
                  <l>No worſe them take, then I haue ment:</l>
                  <l>That after thei be laied in graue,</l>
                  <l>Their ſoules maie ioye their liues well ſpent,</l>
                  <l>God graunt likewiſe that you maie ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my head ſuche heeres to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="subpart">
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Would to God I were <hi>Acteon,</hi> that
<hi>Diana</hi> did diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>To walke the Foreſt vp and doune, whereas my ladie lies:</l>
               <l>An Harte of heere and hewe, I wiſhe that I were ſo,</l>
               <l>So that my Ladie knewe me, onely and no mo.</l>
               <l>The ſhalyng Nutts and Maſte, that falleth from the tree,</l>
               <l>Should well ſuffice for my repaſt, might I my ladie
ſee:</l>
               <l>It ſhould not greue me, there in froſt, to lye vpon the
grounde,</l>
               <l>Delite ſhould eaſly quite the coſte, what euill ſo that
I founde.</l>
               <l>Sometyme that I might ſaie, when I ſawe her alone,</l>
               <l>Beholde, ſee yonder ſlaue aldaie, that walketh the woodds
alone,</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M.B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="subpart">
               <lg>
                  <l>WHy ſhould I lenger long to liue,</l>
                  <l>In this deſeaſe of fantaſie,</l>
                  <l>Sins fortune doeth not ceaſe to giue,</l>
                  <l>Things to my mynde moſte contrarie.</l>
                  <l>And at my ioyes doeth lowre and froune,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe hath tourned them vpſidoune.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:5735:28"/>
                  <l>Affrende I had to me moſte dere,</l>
                  <l>And of long tyme faithfull and iuſte:</l>
                  <l>There was no one, my harte ſo nere,</l>
                  <l>Nor one in whom I had more truſte.</l>
                  <l>Whom now of late without cauſe why,</l>
                  <l>Fortune hath made my enemie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The graſſe me thinks ſhould growe in ſkie</l>
                  <l>The ſtarres, vnto the yearth cleaue faſte:</l>
                  <l>The water ſtreame ſhould paſſe awrie,</l>
                  <l>The winds ſhould leue their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gt of blaſt.</l>
                  <l>The Sonne and Moone by one aſſent,</l>
                  <l>Should bothe forſake the firmament.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fiſhe in ayer ſhould flie with ſinne,</l>
                  <l>The foules in floud ſhould bryng forth fry</l>
                  <l>All thyngs me thinks ſhould erſt beginne,</l>
                  <l>To take their courſe vnnaturally.</l>
                  <l>Afore my frende ſhould alter ſo,</l>
                  <l>Without a cauſe to bee my foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſuche is Fortunes hate I ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Suche is her will on me to wreake:</l>
                  <l>Suche ſpite ſhe hath at me alwaie,</l>
                  <l>And ceaſſeth not my harte to breake.</l>
                  <l>With ſuche diſpite of crueltie,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore then longer liue ſhould I.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="subpart">
               <head>47. Prudens. The historie of Damacles, &amp;
Dioniſe.</head>
               <l>WHoſo is ſet in princly trone, and craueth rule to
beare,</l>
               <l>Is ſtill beſet on euery ſide, with perill and with
feare.</l>
               <l>High trees by ſtormie winds are ſhakt, &amp; rent vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>and flaſhy flaks of lightnings flames on turrets do
robou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>When little ſhrubs in ſauetie lurke, in couert all
alowe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5735:29"/>And freſhly floriſhe in their kynde, what
euer winde doe blowe.</l>
               <l>The cruell kyng of <hi>Sciſily</hi> who fearyng Barbars
hands,</l>
               <l>Was wont to ſinge his beard hym ſelf, with cole and fire
brands.</l>
               <l>Hath taught vs this, the proofe whereof, fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l plainly we maye
ſee.</l>
               <l>Was neuer thyng more liuely touched to ſhewe it ſo to
bee.</l>
               <l>This kyng did ſeme to <hi>Damacles,</hi> to be the happieſt
wight,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he thought none like to hym, in power or in might.</l>
               <l>Who did alone ſo farre excell the reſt in his degree,</l>
               <l>As doeth the Sunne in brightnes cleare, the darkeſt ſtarre
we ſee.</l>
               <l>Wilt thou (then ſaid this cruell kyng) proue this my preſent
ſtate</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſe thou ſhalt this ſeate of myne, and ſo be
fortunate.</l>
               <l>Full gladly then this <hi>Damacles,</hi> this proferd honour
tooke,</l>
               <l>And ſhootyng at a princely life, his quiet reſt
forſooke.</l>
               <l>In honours ſeate then was he plaſt, accordyng to his
will,</l>
               <l>Forthwith a banquet was preparde, that he might feaſt his
fill.</l>
               <l>Nothyng did want wherein twas thought, that he would take
delite,</l>
               <l>To feede his eye, to fill his mouthe, or pleaſe the
appetite.</l>
               <l>Suche ſtore of plate, I thinke in Grece, there ſcarſly was
ſo much</l>
               <l>His ſeruitours did Angels ſeme, their paſſyng ſhape
was ſuche.</l>
               <l>No daintie diſhe but there it was, and thereof was ſuche
ſtore,</l>
               <l>That throughout Grece ſo princly chere, was neuer ſeen
before.</l>
               <l>Thus while in po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe and pleaſures ſeate, this
<hi>Damacles</hi> was plaſt,</l>
               <l>And did beginne with gladſome harte, eche daintie diſhe to
taſte.</l>
               <l>At length by chaunce caſt vp his eyes, and gan the houſe to
vewe,</l>
               <l>And ſawe a ſight that hym enforſt, his princly ſtate to
rewe.</l>
               <l>A ſworde forſoth with dounward point, that had no ſtronger
thred</l>
               <l>Then one horſe heere that peiſed it, direct vpon his
head.</l>
               <l>Wherewith he was ſo ſore amaſde, and ſhooke in euery
parte,</l>
               <l>As though the ſworde that hong aboue, had ſtroke hym to the
hart</l>
               <l>Then all their pleaſures toke their leaue, &amp; ſorowe came
in place,</l>
               <l>His heauie harte the teares declared, that trickled doune his
face.</l>
               <l>And then forthwith with ſobbing voice, beſought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of
grace,</l>
               <l>That he would licens hym with ſpeede, to depart out of that
place.</l>
               <l>And ſaied that he full long enough, had tried now with
feare,</l>
               <l>What tis to be a happie man, and princly rule to beare.</l>
               <l>This deede of thyne oh <hi>Dioniſe,</hi> deſerues immortall
fame,</l>
               <l>This deede ſhall alwaies liue with praiſe, though thou
didſt liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhame.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:5735:29"/>Whereby bothe kyngs be put in minde, their
dangers to be great</l>
               <l>And ſubiects be forbid to clime, high ſtepps of honours
ſeate.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="subpart">
               <head>48. Fortitude. A yong man of Aegipt, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerian.</head>
               <l>EChe one deſerues great praiſe to haue, but yet not like I
think,</l>
               <l>Bothe he that can ſuſtain the yoke of paines, &amp; doeth
not ſhrink</l>
               <l>And he whom <hi>Cupids</hi> couert crafte, can nothyng moue at
all,</l>
               <l>Into the harde and tangled knotts, of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> ſnares
to fall.</l>
               <l>Beſturre you then who ſo delights, in vertues race to
ronne,</l>
               <l>The fliyng boye with bowe ibent, by ſtrength to ouercome.</l>
               <l>As one did once when he was yong, and in his tender daies,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtout and noble deede of his, hath got immortall
praiſe.</l>
               <l>The wicked Romaines did purſue, the ſely Chriſtians
than,</l>
               <l>What tyme <hi>Valerian</hi> Emperour was, a wicked cruell
man.</l>
               <l>Who ſpared not with bloudy draughts, to que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che his owne
deſire</l>
               <l>Diſpatchyng all that ſtucke to Chriſt, with hotte
conſumyng fire.</l>
               <l>At length a man, of tender yeres, was brought before his
ſight,</l>
               <l>Suche one as Nature ſemed to make, a witneſſe of her
might.</l>
               <l>For euery parte ſo well was ſet, that nothyng was
depraued,</l>
               <l>So that the cruell kyng hym ſelf, would gladly haue hym
ſaued.</l>
               <l>So loth he was to ſee a woorke, ſo rare of Naturs power,</l>
               <l>So finely built ſo ſodainly, deſtroied within an
hower.</l>
               <l>Then meanes he ſought to ouercome, or winne hym at the
leſt,</l>
               <l>To ſlip from Chriſte, whom he before had earneſtly
profeſt.</l>
               <l>A bedde preparde, ſo finely deckt, ſuche diuers pleaſaunt
ſmels,</l>
               <l>That well it might appeare a place, where pleaſure onely
dwells.</l>
               <l>By hym he laied a naked wenche, a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> darlyng
ſure,</l>
               <l>With ſugred ſpeache &amp; louely toyes, that might his minde
allure.</l>
               <l>Such wanton lewres as theſe he thought, might eaſſy him
entiſe,</l>
               <l>Which things he knewe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> luſtie youth, had alwaies been in
priſe.</l>
               <l>Suche waies I thinke the Gods themſelues, could haue inuented
none,</l>
               <l>For flatteryng <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> ouercoms, the ſenſes euery
chone,</l>
               <l>And he hym ſelf was euen at point, to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> to
conſent,</l>
               <l>Had not his ſtout and manly mynde, reſiſted his
entent.</l>
               <l>When he perceiued his fleſhe to yelde, to pleaſures wanton
toyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:5735:30"/>And was by ſleight almoſte prouoked, to
taſt of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> ioyes.</l>
               <l>More cruell to hym ſelf then thoſe, that glad would hym
vndoo,</l>
               <l>With bloudie tooth his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der tong, bote quite and cleane in
twoo.</l>
               <l>Thus was the paine ſo paſſyng greate, of this his bloudie
bitte,</l>
               <l>That all the fire and carnall luſt, was quenched euery
whitte.</l>
               <l>Doe ill and all thy pleaſures then, full ſone will paſſe
awaie,</l>
               <l>But yet the ſhame of thoſe thy deedes, will neuermore
decaie.</l>
               <l>Do well &amp; though thy paines be great, yet ſone eche one
wil ceaſe,</l>
               <l>But yet, the praiſe of thoſe thy deedes will euermore
increaſe.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="subpart">
               <head>49. Iustice. Zaleuch and his Sonne.</head>
               <l>LEt rulers make moſt perfect lawes, to rule both great &amp;
ſmal</l>
               <l>If thei them ſelues obeye them not, it boteth not at all.</l>
               <l>As lawes be nought but rulers dome, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining egall might,</l>
               <l>So rulers ſhould be ſpeakyng lawes, to rule by line of
right.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zaleuch</hi> the Prince of <hi>Locrine</hi> once, appointed
by decree,</l>
               <l>Eche lecherer ſhould be puniſhed, with loſſe of either
eye.</l>
               <l>His ſonne by chaunce offended firſt, whiche when his father
ſawe,</l>
               <l>Lorde God how earneſt then was he, to execute the lawe.</l>
               <l>Then ran the people all by flocks, to hym with wepyng eyes,</l>
               <l>Not one emong the rout therewas, but pardon, pardon cries.</l>
               <l>By whoſe outcries and earneſt ſute, his ſonne in hope
did ſtande,</l>
               <l>That he thereby ſhould then obtaine, ſome pardon at his
hande.</l>
               <l>But all in vaine for he is founde, to be the man he was.</l>
               <l>And maketh haſt ſo muche the more, to haue the lawe to
paſſe.</l>
               <l>The people yet renued their ſute, in hope of ſome
relief,</l>
               <l>Whoſe faces all beſprent with teares, did teſtifie their
grief.</l>
               <l>And cried all for pities ſake, yelde now to our requeſt,</l>
               <l>If all you will not cleane remit, yet eaſe the paine at
leſt.</l>
               <l>Then ſomewhat was the father moued, with all the peoples
voice</l>
               <l>And euery man did giue a ſhoote, to ſhewe thei did
reioyce.</l>
               <l>Well then quoth he it ſhalbe thus, the lawe ſhalbe
fufilde.</l>
               <l>And yet my ſonne ſhall fauour haue, accordyng as you
wilde.</l>
               <l>One eye of his ſhalbe pulde out, thus hath his leudneſſe
got,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe ſo ſhall one of myne, though I deſerue it
not.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5735:30"/>This worde no ſoner was pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cde, but
ſtrait y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deede was doen,</l>
               <l>Twoo eyes, no mo were left, betwene the father and the
ſonne.</l>
               <l>Saie now who can, and on my faithe <hi>Apollo</hi> he
ſhalbe,</l>
               <l>Was he more gentle father now? or iuſter Iudge trowe ye.</l>
               <l>This man would not his lawes belike, the webbs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiders
weue,</l>
               <l>Wherein thei lurke when thei entende, the ſimple to
deceiue.</l>
               <l>Wherewith ſmall flies full ſone be caught, &amp; tangled ere
thei wiſt,</l>
               <l>When greate ones flie and ſcape awaie, &amp; breake them as
thei liſt.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="subpart">
               <head>50. Temperaunce. Spurina and the Romaine Ladies.</head>
               <l>IF nature beare thee ſo great loue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhe in thee haue
beautie plaſt</l>
               <l>Full harde it is as we doe proue, to kepe the body cleane &amp;
chaſt:</l>
               <l>Twixt comelineſſe and chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>A deadly ſtrife is thought to be.</l>
               <l>For beautie whiche ſome men ſuppoſe to be, as twere a
golden ill,</l>
               <l>Prouoketh ſtrief and many foes, that ſeke on her to worke
her wil</l>
               <l>Aſſaults to tounes if many make,</l>
               <l>No toune ſo ſtrong but maie be take.</l>
               <l>And this <hi>Spurina</hi> witneſſe can, who did for beautie
beare the bell,</l>
               <l>So cleane a wight ſo comly made, no dame in Rome but loued
wel</l>
               <l>Not one could cole her hote deſire,</l>
               <l>So burnyng was the flame of fire.</l>
               <l>Like as when baite caſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floud, forthwith doeth cauſe
the fiſhes come,</l>
               <l>That pleaſantly before did plaie, now preſently to death to
runne.</l>
               <l>For when thei ſee the baite to fall,</l>
               <l>Straight waie thei ſwallowe hooke and all.</l>
               <l>So when <hi>Spurina</hi> thei did ſee, to hym thei flocked out
of hande,</l>
               <l>She happeſt dame was thought to be, that in his fauour moſte
did ſtande.</l>
               <l>Not knowyng vnder ſweete deceits,</l>
               <l>How <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> hids her poyſoned baits.</l>
               <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſawe them thus to rage, whom loue had linked in
his chain,</l>
               <l>This means he ſought for to aſwage, theſe ladies of their
greuous pain.</l>
               <l>His ſhape intendyng to diſgrace,</l>
               <l>With many wounds he ſkotch his face.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:5735:31"/>By whiche his deede it came to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſemed an angel bright</l>
               <l>Euen now ſo cleane diſfigured was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he became a
ſothſom wight.</l>
               <l>And rather had be foule and chaſt,</l>
               <l>Then faire, and filthie ioyes to taſt.</l>
               <l>What pen ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> write, or to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g expreſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy praiſes
of this deede,</l>
               <l>My think that God can do no leſſe, then graunt him heauen
for his meede.</l>
               <l>Who for to ſaue hym ſelf vpright,</l>
               <l>Hym ſelf hath firſt deſtroyed quite.</l>
               <trailer>Finis</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ꝙ <hi>F. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="subpart">
               <head>51. Abunche of herbes and flowers.</head>
               <l>IF y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eche flower, the godds haue framed, are ſhapt by
ſacred ſkill</l>
               <l>Were as I would (no wrong to wiſhe) &amp; myne to weare at
will.</l>
               <l>Or els eche tree, with luſtie top, would lende me leaue to
loue,</l>
               <l>With ſpriggs diſplaied to ſpread my ſute, a wailing hart
to proue</l>
               <l>Vpon my helme ſone ſhould you ſee, my hedde aduaunced
hie,</l>
               <l>Some ſlipp for ſolace there to ſett, and weare the ſame
would I.</l>
               <l>Yet would I not for greate delight, the Daiſes ſtrange
deſire,</l>
               <l>The Lillie would not like my luſt nor Roſe would I
require.</l>
               <l>The Marigould might growe for me, Roſemary well might
reſte,</l>
               <l>The Fenell to that is more fit, for ſome vnfrendly geſt.</l>
               <l>Nor Cowſlopps would I craue at all, ſometymes thei ſeme to
coy</l>
               <l>Some ioly youth the Gelliflower, eſtemeth for his ioye.</l>
               <l>The Lauender ſometymes aloft, alures the lookers eyes,</l>
               <l>The Paunſie ſhall not haue the praiſe, where I may geue
the priſe</l>
               <l>And thus no flower my fanſie feeds, as liketh ſo my
luſte,</l>
               <l>As that I maie ſubiect my ſelf, to toyes of tickle
truſte.</l>
               <l>For flowers though thei be faire and freſh, of ſent
excelling ſwete</l>
               <l>Yet growe thei on the ground belowe, we tred them with our
fete</l>
               <l>And ſhall I then goe ſtoupe to ſuche? or els go ſeke to
thoſe,</l>
               <l>Shall flowers enforſe me once to faune, for feare of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds or
foes.</l>
               <l>Yet rather yelde I to the right, as reaſon hath
aſſignde,</l>
               <l>Myne authour ſaied there was no ſalue, in flowers for me to
finde.</l>
               <l>And yet perhapps ſome tree there is, to ſhroud me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
ſhower,</l>
               <l>That with her armes maie ſalue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, that yeldeth to
her power.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5735:31"/>Where I maie finde ſome pleaſant ſhade, to
ſalue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne</l>
               <l>Eche thyng w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee that reaſon hath, vnto the trees doe
runne.</l>
               <l>Bothe men &amp; beaſts ſuche ſoules as fly, the
treaſures are the trees</l>
               <l>And for my part when braunches fall, I wiſhe no other
fees.</l>
               <l>But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtormes beſet me round, ſuche ſuccor God
me ſende,</l>
               <l>That I maie finde a frendly tree, that will me well defende.</l>
               <l>No tree there is whiche yelds no good, to ſome that doe it
ſeke</l>
               <l>And as thei are of diuers kynds, their vſes are vnlike.</l>
               <l>The Eue tree ſerues the Bowiers turne, the Aſh the Coupers
art,</l>
               <l>The puiſant Oke doeth make the poſt, the Pine ſome other
part.</l>
               <l>The Elme doeth helpe to hide the birds, in wearie winters
night,</l>
               <l>The Briers I geſſe are nothyng worth, thei ſerue but for
deſpight</l>
               <l>The willowe wiſht I farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hens, good will deſerue no
wrong,</l>
               <l>The Sallowe well maie ſerue their ſtates, that ſyng ſo
ſad a ſong.</l>
               <l>The Boxe and Beche eche for hymſelf, aboue the reſte doeth
boſte,</l>
               <l>The Eglantine for pleaſure oft, is pricked vpon the
poſte.</l>
               <l>The Hauthorne ſo is had in priſe, the Baies doe beare the
bell,</l>
               <l>And that theſe Baies did bryng no bliſſe, I like it not
ſo well.</l>
               <l>As erſt I doe that ſemely tree, by whiche thoſe Baies I
founde,</l>
               <l>And where withall vnwittyngly, I tooke ſo greate a wounde.</l>
               <l>As if the tree by whiche I lent, doeth lende me no relief,</l>
               <l>There is no helpe but doune I fall, ſo greate is growne my
grief.</l>
               <l>And therefore at the laſt I craue, this fauour for to
finde,</l>
               <l>When euery tree that here is told, beginns to growe vnkinde.</l>
               <l>The B. for beautie whom I boſte, and ſhall aboue the
reſt,</l>
               <l>That B. maie take me to her truſt, for B. doeth pleaſe me
beſt.</l>
               <l>It liks me well to walke the waie, where B. doeth kepe her
bower</l>
               <l>And when it raines to B. I ronne to ſaue me from the
ſhower.</l>
               <l>This brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che of B. whiche here I meane, to kepe I chiefly
craue,</l>
               <l>At becke vnto this B. I bowe, to ſarue that beautie braue.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſaie the tyme doeth paſſe, the tale to
tedious is,</l>
               <l>Though loth to leaue, yet leaue I muſt, and ſaie no more but
this,</l>
               <l>I wiſhe this B. I might embrace, when as the ſame I
ſee,</l>
               <l>A league for life then I require, betwene this B. and me.</l>
               <l>And though vnworthy, yet good will, doeth worke the waie
herein</l>
               <l>And B. hath brought the ſame about, whiche beautie did
begin.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="subpart">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:5735:32"/>
               <head>52. Now mortall man beholde and ſee, This worlde is but a
vanitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHo ſhall profoundly way or ſcan, the aſſured ſtate
of man,</l>
                  <l>Shall well perceiue by reaſon than:</l>
                  <l>That where is no ſtabilitie, remaineth nought but
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For what eſtate is there think ye, throughly content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his
degre,</l>
                  <l>Whereby we maie right clerely ſee:</l>
                  <l>That in this vale of miſerie, remaineth nought but
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The great men wiſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane eſtate, meane men again
their ſtate doe hate,</l>
                  <l>Old men thinke children fortunate:</l>
                  <l>A boye a man would faineſt be, thus wandreth man in
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey man doth daily ſwell, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great deſire in
court to dwel</l>
                  <l>The Courtier thinks hym nothyng well:</l>
                  <l>Till he from court, in countrey be, he wandreth ſo in
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſea doeth toſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts brains, to wiſh a
farme &amp; leue thoſe pains,</l>
                  <l>The Farmer gapeth at marchantes gaines:</l>
                  <l>Thus no man can contented be, he wandreth ſo in vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thou haue lands or goods great ſtore, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider thou thy
charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>Since thou muſt make account therefore:</l>
                  <l>Thei are not thine but lent to thee, and yet thei are but
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thou be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or faire of face, ſicknes or age doth
both diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Then be not proude in any caſe:</l>
                  <l>For how can there more folly be, then for to boſt of
vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now finally be not infect, with worldly cares, but haue
reſpect,</l>
                  <l>How God rewardeth his true electe:</l>
                  <l>With glorious felicitie: free from all worldly vanitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Thorn.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="subpart">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:5735:32"/>
               <head>53. Incommendation of Muſick.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHere gripyng grief the hart would wound &amp; dolfull domps
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppreſſe</l>
                  <l>There Muſick with her ſiluer ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, is wont with ſpede
to giue redreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Of troubled minde for euery ſore, ſwete Muſick hath a
ſalue therfore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In ioye it maks our mirth abound, in grief it chers our heauy
ſprights,</l>
                  <l>The carefull head releaſe hath found, by Muſicks
pleaſant ſwete delights</l>
                  <l>Our ſences, what ſhould I ſaie more, are ſubiect vnto
Muſicks lore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Godds by Muſick hath their praie, the foule therein
doeth ioye,</l>
                  <l>For as the Romaine Poets ſaie, in ſeas whom Pirats would
deſtroye,</l>
                  <l>A Dolphin ſaued from death moſte ſharpe, Arion plaiyng
on his harpe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A heauenly gift, that turnes the minde, like as the ſterne
doth rule the ſhip,</l>
                  <l>Muſick whom the Gods aſſignde to comfort man, whom cares
would nip,</l>
                  <l>Sith thou both ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; beaſt doeſt moue, what wiſeman
then wil thee reproue.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M Edwards.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="subpart">
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen ſage <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> ſailed by,</l>
                  <l>The perillous ſeas, where <hi>Cirens</hi> ſyng:</l>
                  <l>Hym ſelf vnto the maſt did tye,</l>
                  <l>Leſt their alluryng tunes might bryng,</l>
                  <l>His mynde on maze and make hym ſtaie,</l>
                  <l>And he with his become their praie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> O thou valiant wight,</l>
                  <l>It ſemed dame <hi>Circes</hi> loued thee well:</l>
                  <l>What tyme ſhe told, to thee aright.</l>
                  <l>The ſeas wherein the <hi>Sirens</hi> dwell.</l>
                  <l>By meane where, againſt thy faile,</l>
                  <l>Their ſubtill ſonges, could not preuaile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were thou amongs vs here againe,</l>
                  <l>And heard our <hi>Sirens</hi> melodie:</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Circes</hi> ſkill nor yet thy braine,</l>
                  <l>Could kepe thee from their trecherie.</l>
                  <l>Suche <hi>Sirens</hi> haue we now adaies,</l>
                  <l>That tempt vs by a thouſande waies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:5735:33"/>
                  <l>Thei ſyng thei daunce, thei ſport, thei plaie</l>
                  <l>Thei humbly fall vpon their knees:</l>
                  <l>Thei ſigh, thei ſobb, thei prate, thei praie,</l>
                  <l>With ſuche diſſemblyng ſhifts as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Thei calculate, thei chaunt, thei charme,</l>
                  <l>To conquere vs that meane no harme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good ladies all letts ioyne in one,</l>
                  <l>And baniſhe cleane this <hi>Siren</hi> kinde:</l>
                  <l>What nede we yelde, to heare their mone,</l>
                  <l>Since their deceipt we daiely finde.</l>
                  <l>Let not your harts to them apply,</l>
                  <l>Defie them all for ſo will I.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And if where <hi>Circes</hi> now doeth dwell,</l>
                  <l>You wiſht you witt aduiſe, to learne:</l>
                  <l>Loe I am ſhe that beſt can tell,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Sirens</hi> ſonges and them diſcerne.</l>
                  <l>For why experience yeldeth ſkill,</l>
                  <l>To me that ſcapt that <hi>Sirens</hi> ill.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Bew.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="subpart">
               <head>55. Findyng no ioye, he deſireth death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Cony in his caue, the Feret doeth anoye,</l>
                  <l>And fleyng thence his life to ſaue, him ſelf he doeth
deſtroye.</l>
                  <l>His Berrie rounde about beſett, with hunters ſnares,</l>
                  <l>So that when he to ſcape ſtarts out, is caught therein
vnwares,</l>
                  <l>Like choiſe poore man haue I to bide and reſt in loue,</l>
                  <l>Or els from thence to ſtart, and ſtill as bad a death to
proue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee, in loue to reſt, vnkindneſſe doeth
purſue,</l>
                  <l>To rent the harte out of his breaſt, whiche is a louer
true.</l>
                  <l>And if from loue I ſtarte, as one that loue forſaks,</l>
                  <l>Then penſiue thoughts my harte doeth perſe, &amp; ſo my
life it taks.</l>
                  <l>Thus then to fly or bide, harde is the choiſe to
chuſe,</l>
                  <l>Since death hath ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pde, &amp; trea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hed eche ſide, &amp;
ſaith life now refuſe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:5735:33"/>
                  <l>Content I am therefore, my life therein to ſpende,</l>
                  <l>And death I take a ſalue for ſore, my wearie daies to
ende.</l>
                  <l>And thus I you requeſt, that faithfull loue
profeſſe,</l>
                  <l>When carcas caſed is in cheſt, and bodie laied on
hears.</l>
                  <l>Your briniſhe teares to ſaue, ſuche as my corſe
ſhall moue,</l>
                  <l>And therewith write vpon my graue, behold the force of
loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Hope well and haue well.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN hope the Shipman hoiſeth ſaile, in hope of paſſage
good,</l>
                  <l>In hope of health the ſickly man, doeth ſuffer loſſe
of bloud.</l>
                  <l>In hope the priſoner linckt in chaines, hopes libertie to
finde,</l>
                  <l>Thus hope breds helth &amp; helth breds eaſe, to euery
troubled mynd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In hope deſire getts victorie, in hope greate comfort
ſpryngs,</l>
                  <l>In hope the louer liues in ioyes, he feares no dreadfull
flyngs:</l>
                  <l>In hope we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iue and maie abide, ſuche ſtormes as are
aſſignde,</l>
                  <l>Thus hope breds helth, &amp; helth breds eaſe, to euery
troubled mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In hope we eaſely ſuffer harme, in hope of future
tyme,</l>
                  <l>In hope of fruite, the pain ſemes ſwete, that to the tree
doeth clime</l>
                  <l>In hope of loue ſuche glory growes, as now by profe I
finde:</l>
                  <l>That hope breds helth, &amp; helth breds eaſe to euery
troubled minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>He repenteth his folly.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt mine eyes did vew, &amp; marke thy beautie faire
for to behold,</l>
                  <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myne eares, gan firſt to harke, the pleaſant
words y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou me told</l>
                  <l>I would as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had been free, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eares to heare, &amp;
eyes to ſe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when my hands did handle oft, that might thee kepe in
memorie,</l>
                  <l>And when my feete had gone ſo ſofte, to finde and haue thy
companie,</l>
                  <l>I would eche hande a foote had been, and eke eche foote, a
hand ſo ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:5735:34"/>
                  <l>And when in minde I did conſent, to followe thus my
fanſies will,</l>
                  <l>And when my harte did firſt relent, to taſt ſuche baite
my ſelf to ſpill,</l>
                  <l>I would my harte had been as thine, or els thy harte as ſoft
as myne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould not I ſuche cauſe haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to wiſh this
mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrus ſight to ſe,</l>
                  <l>Ne thou alas that madeſt the wounde, ſhould not deny me
remedy,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould one will in bothe remain, to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t one hart
whiche now is twaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>He requeſteth ſome frendly comfort affirmyng his
conſtancie.</head>
               <l>THe mountaines hie whoſe loftie topps, doeth mete the hautie
ſky</l>
               <l>The craggie rocke that to the ſea, free paſſage doeth
deny,</l>
               <l>The aged Oke that doeth reſiſt, the force of bluſtryng
blaſt,</l>
               <l>The pleaſaunt herbe that euery where, a fragrant ſmell doeth
caſt.</l>
               <l>The Lyons forſe whoſe courage ſtout, declares a princlike
might,</l>
               <l>The Eagle that for worthineſſe, is borne of kyngs in
fight:</l>
               <l>The Serpent eke whoſe poiſoned waies, doeth belche out venim
vile,</l>
               <l>The lothſome Tode that ſhunneth light, and liueth in
exile.</l>
               <l>Theſe theſe I ſaie and thouſands more, by trackt of tyme
decaie,</l>
               <l>And like to tyme doe quite conſume, and vade from forme to
claie:</l>
               <l>But my true harte and ſeruice vowed, ſhall laſt tyme out
of minde,</l>
               <l>And ſtill remaine as thine by dome, as <hi>Cupid</hi> hath
aſſignde.</l>
               <l>My faithe loe here I vowe to thee, my trothe thou knoweſt
right well,</l>
               <l>My goods my frends, my life is thine, what nede I more to
tell?</l>
               <l>I am not myne but thine I vowe, thy heſts I will obeye,</l>
               <l>And ſerue thee as a ſeruaunt ought, in pleaſyng if I
maie:</l>
               <l>And ſith I haue no fliyng wings, to ſee thee as I
wiſhe,</l>
               <l>Ne finnes to cut the ſiluer ſtreames, as doeth the glidyng
fiſhe.</l>
               <l>Wherefore leaue now forgetfulneſſe, and ſende againe to
me,</l>
               <l>And ſtraine thy azured vaines to write, that I maie greetyng
ſee:</l>
               <l>And thus farewell more deare to me, then chiefeſt frende I
haue,</l>
               <l>Whoſe loue in harte I minde to ſhrine, till death his fee
doe craue.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwards.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:5735:34"/>
               <head>He complaineth his miſhapp.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SHall rigor raigne where youth hath ron, ſhall fanſie now
forſake.</l>
                  <l>Shall fortune loſe that fauour wonne, ſhall not your anger
flake:</l>
                  <l>Shall hatefull harte be had in you, that frendly did
pretende,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſlipper thoughts and faithe vntrue, that harte of
yours defende</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall nature ſhewe your beautie faire, that gentle ſemes
to be,</l>
                  <l>Shall frowardneſſe, your fancies ayer, be of more force
then ſhe:</l>
                  <l>Shall now diſdaine the dragg of death, direct and leade the
waie,</l>
                  <l>Shall all the imps vpon the yearth, reioyce at my decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall this the ſeruice of my youth, haue ſuche reward at
laſt,</l>
                  <l>Shall I receiue rigor for ruth, and be from fauour caſt:</l>
                  <l>Shall I therefore berent my harte, with wights that wiſhe to
dye,</l>
                  <l>Or ſhall I bathe my ſelf with teares, to feede your fickle
eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No no I ſhall in paine lye ſtill, with Turtle doue moſte
true,</l>
                  <l>And vowe my ſelf to witt and will, their counſels, to
enſue:</l>
                  <l>Good Ladies all that louers be, your helpe hereto
purtende,</l>
                  <l>Giue place to witt, let reaſon ſeme, your enemie to
defende.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Leſt that you thinke as I haue thought, your ſelf to
ſtriue in vaine,</l>
                  <l>And ſo to be in thraldome brought, with me to ſuffer
paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M.H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>No foe to a flatterer.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Would it were not as I thinke, I would it were not
ſo,</l>
                  <l>I am not blinde although I winke, I feele what winds doe
blowe:</l>
                  <l>I knowe where craft, with ſmilyng cheare, creps into bloudy
breſt,</l>
                  <l>I heare how fained ſpeache, ſpeaks faire, where hatred is
poſſeſt.</l>
                  <l>I ſe the Serpent lye and Iurck, vnder the grene alowe,</l>
                  <l>I ſee hym watche a tyme, to worke, his poyſon to
beſtowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In frendly looks ſuche fraude is founde, as faithe for feare
is fleade,</l>
                  <l>And frendſhip hath receiued ſuche wounde, as he is
almoſte deade,</l>
                  <l>And hatefull harte with malice greate, ſo boyles in cankerd
minde:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:5735:35"/>That flatteries flearyng in my face, had
almoſte made me blinde,</l>
                  <l>But now I ſee all is not golde, that glittereth in the
eye,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet ſuche frends as thei profeſſe, as now by profe I
finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though ſecret ſpight by craft, hath made a coate of
Panters ſkin,</l>
                  <l>And thinks to finde me in the ſhade, by ſleight to wrapp
me in,</l>
                  <l>Yet God be praiſed my eye is cleare, and can beholde the
Sonne:</l>
                  <l>When falſhood dares not once appeare, to ende that he
begonne,</l>
                  <l>Thus tyme ſhall trie the thyng amiſſe, whiche God ſone
ſhortly ſende.</l>
                  <l>And turne the hatte that fained is, to be a faithfull
frende.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Spider with greate ſkill, doeth trauell daie by
daie,</l>
                  <l>His limmes no tyme, lye ſtill to ſet his houſe in
ſtaie:</l>
                  <l>And when he hath it wrought, thinkyng therein to raigne,</l>
                  <l>A blaſt of winde vnthought, doeth driue it doune againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The profe whereof is true, to make his worke indure,</l>
                  <l>He paines hym ſelf a newe, in hope to dwell more ſure:</l>
                  <l>Or in ſome ſecret place, a corner of the wall,</l>
                  <l>He trauaileth a ſpare, to builde and reſt with all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His pleaſure ſwete to ſtaie, when he to reſt is
bent,</l>
                  <l>An vgly ſhamble Flie, approcheth to his tent:</l>
                  <l>And there entends by forſe, his labours greate to win,</l>
                  <l>Or els to yelde his corſe, by fatall death therein.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus is the Spiders neſt, from tyme to tyme throwne
downe,</l>
                  <l>And he to labour preſt, with endles pains vnknowne:</l>
                  <l>So ſuche as louers be, like trauell doe attaine,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe endles works ye ſee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er alwaies full of paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Hunis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſubtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y ſleights, that worldly men doe worke,</l>
                  <l>The fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly ſhowes vnder whoſe ſhade, moſt craft doth
ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lurke</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:5735:35"/>Enforceth me alas, with yernfull voice to
ſaie,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wily heads that ſeeks, the ſimple mans
decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The birde that dreds no guile, is ſoneſt caught in
ſnare,</l>
                  <l>Eche gentle harte deuoide of craft, is ſoneſt brought to
care:</l>
                  <l>Good nature ſoneſt trapt, whiche giues me cauſe to
ſaie.</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wily heads that ſeeks, the ſimple mans
decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the ſerpent vile, that lurks vnder the grene,</l>
                  <l>How ſubtelly he ſhrouds hym ſelf, that he maie not be
ſene:</l>
                  <l>And yet his foſters bane, his leryng looks bewraie,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the wily heads that ſeeks, the ſimple mans
decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wo worthe the fainyng looks, one fauour that doe waite,</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the fained frendly harte, that harbours depe
deceit:</l>
                  <l>Wo worthe the Vipers broode, oh chriſe wo worthe I
ſaie,</l>
                  <l>All worldly wily heads that ſeeks, the ſimple mans
decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwards.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <lg>
                  <l>WIth painted ſpeache I liſt not proue, my cunnyng for to
trie,</l>
                  <l>Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et will vſe to fill my penne, with gilefull
flatterie:</l>
                  <l>With pen in hand and harte in breaſt, ſhall faithfull
promiſe make</l>
                  <l>To loue you beſt, and ſerue you moſte, for your great
vertues ſake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince dame Nature hath you deckt, with gifts aboue the
reſt,</l>
                  <l>Let not diſdaine a harbour finde, within your noble
breſt:</l>
                  <l>For loue hath ledd his lawe alike, to men of eche degree,</l>
                  <l>So that the begger with the prince, ſhall loue as well as
he.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I am no prince I muſt confeſſe, nor yet of princes
line,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet a brutiſhe begger borne, that feeds among the
Swine:</l>
                  <l>The fruite ſhall trie the tree at laſt, the bloſſomes
good or no,</l>
                  <l>Then doe not iudge of me the worſe, till you haue tried me
ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As I deſerue, ſo then reward, I make you iudge of all,</l>
                  <l>If I be falſe in worde or deede, let lightnyng thunder
fall:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:5735:36"/>And furies fell with franticke fitts,
bereue and ſtopp my breathe,</l>
                  <l>For an example to the reſt, if I ſhall breake my
faithe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Trie and then truſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe ſainct I ſerue, and haue beſought full oft,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my knees, to ſtande my Goddes good:</l>
                  <l>With hope did holde, my head ſometyme aloft,</l>
                  <l>And fed my faunyng frende, with daintie foode.</l>
                  <l>But now I ſee, that words are nought but winde,</l>
                  <l>The ſweter meate, the ſowrer ſauce I finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus while I helde the Ele by the taile,</l>
                  <l>I had ſome hope, yet neuer wanted feare:</l>
                  <l>Of double dread, that man can neuer faile,</l>
                  <l>That will preſume to take the Wolfe, by the eare.</l>
                  <l>I ſnatche for ſothe, muche like to Eſops dogg,</l>
                  <l>I ſought for fiſhe, and alwaies caught a frogg.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus did I long bite, on the fomyng bitt,</l>
                  <l>Whiche found me plaie enough, vnto my paine:</l>
                  <l>Thus while I loued, I neuer wanted fitt,</l>
                  <l>But liued by loſſe, and ſought no other gaine.</l>
                  <l>But why ſhould I miſlike with Fortunes fetters,</l>
                  <l>Since that the like haue hapt vnto my betters.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Richard Hill.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Complainyng to his frende, he replieth wittely.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>THe fire ſhall freeſe, the froſt ſhall frie the frozen
mountains hie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>what ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thinges ſhal dame nature force, to turne her
courſe awrie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My Ladie hath me left, and taken a newe man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>This is not ſtraunge, it happes oft tymes, the truthe to
ſcan,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her loue then refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>ethe one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:5735:36"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>By ſkilfull meanes I her reclaime, to ſtope vnto my
luer,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche hagard haukes will ſore awaie, of them who can be
fuct.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>With ſiluer bells and hoode, my ioye was her to decke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>She was full gorgd, ſhe would the ſoner giue the
checke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her loue then refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Her chirping lippes would chirp to me, ſwete wordes of her
deſire</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche chirping birdes who euer ſawe, to preach ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n
one brire</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſaied ſhe loued me deſts, and would doe till ſhe
die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſaied in wordes, ſhe thought it not, as tyme doeth
trie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her loue then refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Can no man winne: a woman ſo, to make her loue endure,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To make the Foxe his wiles to leaue, what man will put in
vre,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then there is no choice, but all women will chaunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>As men doe vſe ſo, ſome women doe loue to raunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The more is my paine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>her loue then refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thought ſhe would flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>eche one that hath witt:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>light loue will chaunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Sithe ſlipper gaine falles to my lot, farwell that glidyng
praie</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Sithe that the dice doeth runne a wrie, betimes leaue of thy
plaie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will no more lament, the thyng I maie not haue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Then by exchaunge the loſſe to come, all ſhalt thou
ſaue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Loue will I refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>thereby thou ſhalt gaine:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>With loſſe I will leaue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>ſhe will thee deceiue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>That is not ſtraunge,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then let her raunge.</l>
               </sp>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Edwards.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>No paines comparable to his attempt:</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Hat watche, what we, what want, what wracke?</l>
                  <l>Is due to thoſe that toyle the Seas:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:5735:37"/>Life ledd with loſſe, of paines no
lacke,</l>
                  <l>In ſtormes to winne, muche reſtleſſe caſe.</l>
                  <l>A bedleſſe horde, in ſeas vnreſt,</l>
                  <l>Maie happ to hym, that chaunſeth beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How ſundrie ſounds with lead and line,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the depe, the ſhipman throwes:</l>
                  <l>No foote to ſpare, he cries oft tymes,</l>
                  <l>No nere, when how the maſter blowes.</l>
                  <l>If Neptune frown, all be vndoen,</l>
                  <l>Strait waie the ſhipp, the wrack hath won</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe daungers greate doe oft befall,</l>
                  <l>On thoſe that there vpon the ſande:</l>
                  <l>Iudge of their liues, the beſt who ſhall,</l>
                  <l>How vile it is, fewe vnderſtande.</l>
                  <l>Alacke? who then maie iudge, their game:</l>
                  <l>Not thei, whiche haue not felt the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thei that fall in ſtormes and winde,</l>
                  <l>And daies and yeres haue ſpent therein:</l>
                  <l>Suche well may iudge, ſince profe thei find</l>
                  <l>In rage, no reſt, till calme begin.</l>
                  <l>No more then thoſe, that loue doe faine,</l>
                  <l>Giue iudgement of true louers paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>No pleaſure without ſome paine.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw can the tree but waſt, and wither awaie,</l>
                  <l>That hath not ſometyme comfort of the Sonne:</l>
                  <l>How can that flower but fade, and ſone decaie,</l>
                  <l>That alwaies is with darke clouds ouer ronne.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life, naie death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That feeles eche paine, and knoweth no ioye at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What foodles beaſt can liue long in good plight,</l>
                  <l>Or is it life, where ſences there be none:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:5735:37"/>Or what auaileth eyes without their
light?</l>
                  <l>Or els a tonge, to hym that is alone.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life? naie death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That feeles eche paine, and knowes no ioye at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whereto ſerue eares, if that there be no ſounde,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuche a head, where no deuiſe doeth growe:</l>
                  <l>But all of plaints, ſince ſorrowe is the grounde,</l>
                  <l>Whereby the harte doeth pine in deadly woe.</l>
                  <l>Is this a life, naie death you maie it call,</l>
                  <l>That feeles eche paine, and knows no ioye at all.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ The fruites of fained frendes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN choiſe of frends what happy had I, to chuſe one of
<hi>Cirenes</hi> kinde,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe harpe, whoſe pipe, whoſe melodie, could feede my
eares &amp; make me blinde:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pleaſant noiſe made me forget, that in ſure
truſt was great deceit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In truſt I ſee is treaſon founde, and man to man
deceitfull is,</l>
                  <l>And whereas Treaſure doeth abounde, of flatterers there doe
not miſſe:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe painted ſpeache, and outward ſhowe, doe ſeme as
frends and be not ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Would I haue thought in thee to be, the nature of the
Crokadill,</l>
                  <l>Whiche if a man a ſlepe maie ſee, with bloudy thirſt
deſires to kill:</l>
                  <l>And then with teares a while gan wepe, the death of hym thus
ſlaine a ſlepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O flatterer falſe, thou traitor borne, what miſchief more
might thou deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>Then thy deare frende, to haue in ſcorne, and hym to wounde
in ſondrie wiſe:</l>
                  <l>Whiche ſtill a frende pretends to be, and art not ſo by
profe I ſe.</l>
                  <l>Fie fie, vpon ſuche trechery.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Beyng importunate, at the length, he obtaineth.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>SHall I no waie winne you, to graunt my deſire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>What woman, will graunt you, the thyng you require:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>You onely to loue me, is all that craue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:5735:38"/>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You onely to leaue me, is all I would haue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My deare alas now ſaie not ſo,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To loue you beſt, I muſt ſaie no:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſwifter I followe, then you fly awaie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Swift hauks in their fliyng, oft times miſſe their
pray</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet ſome killeth dedly, that flie to the marke:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall touche no feather, thereof take no carke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet hope ſhall further my deſire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You blowe the coales, and raiſe no fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>To loue is no daunger where true loue is ment,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will loue no ranger, leſt that I repent:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>My loue is no ranger, I make God auow,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>To truſt your ſmoth ſaiyngs, I ſure knowe not how.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſte truthe I meane, as tyme ſhall well trie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>No truthe in men, I oft eſpie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Be ſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Some women maie ſaie naie, and meane loue moſte true,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Some women can make fools, of as wiſe men as you,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>In tyme I ſhall catche you, I knowe when and where:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will ſone diſpatche you, you ſhall not come there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ſpeds at length, that oft haue miſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I am well armed, come when you liſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet will I not flitt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>then plaie on the bitt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>doe ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>beſhrewe me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:5735:38"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet worke your kinde kindly, graunt me loue for loue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will vſe you frendly, as I ſhall you proue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſte cloſe you ſhall finde me, I this doe
proteſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſure you ſhall binde me, to graunt your
requeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>O happie threde now haue I ſponne,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſyng before the conqueſt wonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then, will you ſwarne,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>euen as you deſerue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Loue ſtill,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>yet kill not,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me your man,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <l>come to me than.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Requiryng the fauour of his loue: She aunſwereth
thus.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>WHat death maie be, compared to loue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>What grief therein, now doeſt thou proue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My paines alas who can expreſſe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee no cauſe of heauineſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My Ladies looks, my wo hath wrought:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Then blame thyne eyes that firſt haue ſought,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>I burne alas, and blowe the fire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>A foole conſumes by his deſire,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H,</speaker>
                  <l>come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſugred ſweete, is mixed with gall,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Ladie can not doe with all:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>The more I ſeeke, the leſſe I finde,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſtriue not with the ſtreame and winde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her muſt I loue, although I ſmarte,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>With thy owne ſworde, thou ſlaieſt thy harte:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche pleaſaunt baites, who can refraine,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche beats will ſure brede the greate paine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhal I do than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:5735:39"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her golden beames, myne eyes doe daze,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Vpon the Sonne thou maieſt not gaze:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>She might reward my cruell ſmarte,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>She thinks thou beareſt a fained harte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>She laughs to heare my wofull cries,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Forſake her then, in tyme be wiſe:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>No no alas, that maie not bee,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>No wiſe man then will pitie thee,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do than?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>come out and thou can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>A liuyng death, loe thus I proue,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Suche are the fruts of froward loue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>O that I might her loue once againe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy gaine would not, halfe quite the paine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Her will I loue though ſhe be coye,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>A foole hym ſelf will ſtill anoye:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Who will not die for ſuche a one,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>Be wiſe at length, let her alone:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>I can not doe ſo,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>then be thy owne foe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H.</speaker>
                  <l>what remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ A louers ioye.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Haue no ioye, but dreame of ioye, and ioye to thinke
on ioye,</l>
               <l>A ioye I withſtoode, for to enioye, to finiſhe myne
anoye:</l>
               <l>I hate not without cauſe alas, yet loue I knowe not why,</l>
               <l>I thought to hate, I can not hate, although that I ſhould
die.</l>
               <l>A foe moſte ſwete, a frende moſte ſower, I ioye for to
embrace,</l>
               <l>I hate the wrong and not the wight, that workt my wofull
caſe:</l>
               <l>What thyng it is I knowe not I, but yet a thyng there is,</l>
               <l>That in my fancie ſtill perſwads, there is no other
bliſſe.</l>
               <l>The ioyes of life, the pangs of death, it make me feele eche
daie,</l>
               <l>But life nor death, this humour can deuiſe to weare awaie.</l>
               <l>Faine would I dye, but yet in death no hope I ſee
remaines,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:5735:39"/>And ſhall I liue? ſince life I ſee, a
ſourſe of ſorie paines:</l>
               <l>What is it then that I doe ſeke, what ioye would I
aſpire,</l>
               <l>A thyng that is deuine belike, to high for mans deſire.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>FK.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ The iudgement of deſire.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe liuely Larke did ſtretche her wyng,</l>
                  <l>The meſſenger of mornyng bright:</l>
                  <l>And with her cherefull voyce did ſyng,</l>
                  <l>The daies approche, diſchargyng night.</l>
                  <l>When that Aurora bluſhyng redd,</l>
                  <l>Diſcride the gilt of Thetis bedd:</l>
                  <l>Laradon tan tan, Tedriton teight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I went abroad to take the aire,</l>
                  <l>And in the meadds I mett a knight,</l>
                  <l>Clad in carnation colour faire,</l>
                  <l>I did ſalute the youthfull wight.</l>
                  <l>Of hym I did his name enquire,</l>
                  <l>He ſight and ſaied, I am deſire,</l>
                  <l>Laradon tan tan, Tedriton teight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deſire I did deſire to ſtaie,</l>
                  <l>A while with hym I craued talke:</l>
                  <l>The courteous wight ſaied me no naie,</l>
                  <l>But hande in hande with me did walke.</l>
                  <l>Then in deſire I aſkte againe,</l>
                  <l>What thing did pleaſe, and what did pain</l>
                  <l>Laradon, tan, tan.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He ſmild and thus he anſwered me,</l>
                  <l>Deſire can haue no greater paine:</l>
                  <l>Then for to ſee an other man,</l>
                  <l>The thyng deſired to obtaine.</l>
                  <l>No ioye no greater to then this,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:5735:40"/>Then to inioye what others miſſe,</l>
                  <l>Laridon, tan, tan.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ The complaint of a louer, wearyng Blacke and
Tawnie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Croune of Bayes ſhall that man weare,</l>
                  <l>That triumphs ouer me:</l>
                  <l>For blacke and Tawnie will I weare,</l>
                  <l>Whiche mournyng colours be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The more I folowed on, the more ſhe fled awaie,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Daphne</hi> did full long agone, <hi>Apollos</hi>
wiſhfull praie:</l>
                  <l>The more my plaints reſounde, the leſſe ſhe pities
me,</l>
                  <l>The more I ſaught the leſſe I founde, that myne ſhe
ment to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Melpomeney,</hi> alas with dolefull tunes helpe than,</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>bis</hi> wo worthe on me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> forſaken
man:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Daphnes</hi> baies ſhal that man weare, that
triumphs ouer me,</l>
                  <l>For Blacke &amp; Taunie will I weare, which monrnyng colours
be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Droune me you tricklyng teares, you wailefull wights of
woe,</l>
                  <l>Come help theſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my heares, my rufull happs to
ſhowe:</l>
                  <l>On whom the ſcorchyng flames of loue, doeth feede you
ſe,</l>
                  <l>Ah a lalalantida my deare dame, hath thus tormented me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherefore you Muſes nine, with dolefull tunes helpe
than,</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>Bis</hi> wo worthe on me forſaken man:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Daphnes</hi> Baies ſhall that man weare, that
triumps euer me</l>
                  <l>For Blacke &amp; Taunie will I weare, which mourning colours
be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An Ancres life to leade, with nailes to ſcratche my
graue,</l>
                  <l>Where earthly Wormes on me ſhall fede, is all the ioyes I
craue:</l>
                  <l>And hid my ſelf from ſhame, ſith that myne eyes doe
ſee,</l>
                  <l>Ah a alantida my deare dame, hath thus tormented me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:5735:40"/>And all that preſent be, with dolefull
tunes helpe than:</l>
                  <l>And ſyng <hi>Bis</hi> woe worthe on me, forſaken man.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E.O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ He complaineth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LO heare the man that muſt of loue complaine,</l>
                  <l>Lo heare that ſeas that feeles no kinde of bliſſe:</l>
                  <l>Lo here I ſeke for ioye, and finde but paine,</l>
                  <l>Lo what deſpite can greater be then this?</l>
                  <l>To freze to death, and ſtande yet by the fire,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe that ſhonneth me moſte, I doe deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſhall I ſpeake alas, or ſhall I die,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>By death no helpe, in ſpeache ſome helpe doeth lie:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <l>Then from that breaſt, remoue a Marble minde,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>As I ſee cauſe, ſo are ye like to finde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <l>I yelde my ſelf, what would you more of me,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>You yelde, but for to winne and conquer me,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L.</speaker>
                  <l>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and kill not madame,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <l>Forſake your ſute for ſhame,</l>
                  <l>No no no no, not ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <lg>
                  <l>O happie man, now vaunt thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>That hath this conqueſt gainde:</l>
                  <l>And now doeth liue in greate delight,</l>
                  <l>That was ſo lately painde.</l>
                  <l>Triumph, triumph, triumph, wholouers be</l>
                  <l>Thriſe happie is that woyng,</l>
                  <l>That is not long a doyng,</l>
                  <l>Triumph, triumph, triumph, that hath like victorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:5735:41"/>
               <head>¶ Findyng no relief, he complaineth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN queſt of my relief I finde diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>In recompence of loue, moſte depe diſdaine:</l>
                  <l>My langour is ſuche, words maie not expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſhower of teares, my watriſhe eye doeth raine.</l>
                  <l>I dreame of this, and doe deuine of wo,</l>
                  <l>I wander in the thoughts, of my ſwete fo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I would no peace, the cauſe of warre I flie,</l>
                  <l>I hope, I feare I burne, I chill in froſte:</l>
                  <l>I lye alowe, yet mounts my minde on hie,</l>
                  <l>Thus doubtfull ſtormes, my troubled thoughts haue
toſte,</l>
                  <l>And for my paine, this pleaſure doe I proue.</l>
                  <l>I hate my ſelf, and pine in others loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The worlde I graſpe, yet holde I nought at all,</l>
                  <l>At libertie, I ſeme in priſon pent:</l>
                  <l>I taſte the ſweete, more lower then bitter gall,</l>
                  <l>My ſhipp ſemes ſounde, and yet her ribbs be rent.</l>
                  <l>And out alas, on Fortune falſe I crie,</l>
                  <l>Looke what I craue, that ſtill ſhe doeth denie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bothe life and death, be equall vnto me,</l>
                  <l>I doe deſire to die, yet craue I life,</l>
                  <l>My witts with ſondrie thoughts doe diſagre,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf am with my ſelf at mortall ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>As warmth of ſonne doeth melte the ſiluer Snowe,</l>
                  <l>The heate of loue, beholde conſumes me ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R.H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng in loue, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHat dome is, this I faine would knowe,</l>
                  <l>That demeth all by contraries:</l>
                  <l>What God, or whether height or lowe,</l>
                  <l>Now would I learne ſome warrantiſe.</l>
                  <l>Some ſaie the blinded God aboue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:5735:41"/>Is he that woorketh all by loue:</l>
                  <l>But he that ſtirreth ſtrife, the truthe to tell,</l>
                  <l>I alwaies feele, but knowe not well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some ſaie <hi>Alecto</hi> with her mates,</l>
                  <l>Are thei whiche breedeth all anoye:</l>
                  <l>Who ſitts like Haggs in helliſhe gates,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeks ſtill whom thei maie deſtroye.</l>
                  <l>Some ſaie againe, tis deſtinie,</l>
                  <l>But how it comes, or what it is,</l>
                  <l>I let it paſſe, before I miſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Deſpite doeth alwaies worke my wo,</l>
                  <l>And happ as yet holds hardly ſtill:</l>
                  <l>For feare I ſet my frendſhipp ſo,</l>
                  <l>And thinke againe to reape good will.</l>
                  <l>I doe but ſtriue againſt the winde,</l>
                  <l>For more I ſeeke, the leſſe I finde:</l>
                  <l>And where I ſeeke moſte for to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>There finde I alwaies my deſeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And thus I loue, and doe reape ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Nothyng but hate for my good will.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A louer diſdained, complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF euer man had loue to dearly bought,</l>
                  <l>Lo I am he that plaies within her maze:</l>
                  <l>And finds no waie, to get the ſame I ſought,</l>
                  <l>But as the Dere are driuen vnto the gaze.</l>
                  <l>And to augment the grief of my deſire,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf to burne, I blowe the fire:</l>
                  <l>But ſhall I come ny you,</l>
                  <l>Of forſe I muſt flie you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:5735:42"/>
                  <l>What death alas, maie be compared to this,</l>
                  <l>I plaie within the maze of my ſwete foe:</l>
                  <l>And when I would of her but craue a kis,</l>
                  <l>Diſdaine enforceth her awaie to goe.</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I check: yet doe I twiſte the twine,</l>
                  <l>The pleaſure hers, the paine is myne,</l>
                  <l>But ſhall I come ny you,</l>
                  <l>Of forſe I muſt flie you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You courtly wights, that wants your pleaſant choiſe,</l>
                  <l>Lende me a floud of teares, to waile my chaunce:</l>
                  <l>Happie are thei in loue, that can reioyſe,</l>
                  <l>To their greate paines, where fortune doeth aduaunce</l>
                  <l>But ſith my ſute alas, can not preuaile,</l>
                  <l>Full fraight with care, in grief ſtill will I waile:</l>
                  <l>Sith you will needs flie me,</l>
                  <l>I maie not come ny you.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L.<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng in loue, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF care or ſkill, could conquere vaine deſire,</l>
                  <l>Or reaſons raines, my ſtrong affection ſtaie:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould my ſights, to quiet breaſt retire,</l>
                  <l>And ſhunne ſuche ſignes, as ſecret thoughts
bewraie.</l>
                  <l>Vncomely loue, whiche now lurks in my breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Should ceaſe my grief, through wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s power oppreſt</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But who can leaue, to looke on <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> face?</l>
                  <l>Or yeldeth not, to <hi>Iunos</hi> high eſtate:</l>
                  <l>What witt ſo wiſe, as giues not <hi>Pallas</hi> place,</l>
                  <l>Theſe vertues rare, eche Godds did yelde amate.</l>
                  <l>Saue her alone, who yet on yearth doeth reigne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beauties ſtryng, no Gods can well deſtraine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What worldly wight, can hope for heauenly hire,</l>
                  <l>When onely ſights, muſt make his ſecret mone:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:5735:42"/>A ſilent ſute, doeth ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de to Grace
aſpire,</l>
                  <l>My haples happe, doeth role to reſtles ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Phebe</hi> faire, diſdainde the heauens aboue,</l>
                  <l>To ioye on yearth, her poore <hi>Endimions</hi> loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rare is reward, where none can iuſtly craue,</l>
                  <l>For chaunce is choiſe, where reaſon maks no claime:</l>
                  <l>Yet lucke ſometymes, diſpairyng ſouls doeth ſaue,</l>
                  <l>A happie ſtarre made <hi>Giges</hi> ioye attaine.</l>
                  <l>A ſlauiſhe Smith, of rude and raſcall race,</l>
                  <l>Founde means in tyme, to gaine a Goddes grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then loftie Loue, thy ſacred ſailes aduaunce,</l>
                  <l>My ſithyng ſeas, ſhall flowe with ſtreames of
teares:</l>
                  <l>Amidds diſdaine, driue forthe my dolefull chaunce,</l>
                  <l>A valiaunt minde, no deadly daunger feares.</l>
                  <l>Who loues alofte, and ſetts his harte on hie,</l>
                  <l>Deſerues no paine, though he doe pine and die.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M.B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶A louer reiected, complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe tricklyng teares, that fales along my cheeks,</l>
                  <l>The ſecret ſighs, that ſhowes my inward grief:</l>
                  <l>The preſent paines perforce, that loue aye ſeeks,</l>
                  <l>Bidds me renew, my cares without relief,</l>
                  <l>In wofull ſong in dole diſplaie,</l>
                  <l>My penſiue harte for to bewraie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bewraie thy grief, thou wofull harte with ſpeede,</l>
                  <l>Reſigne thy voyce, to her that cauſde thy woe:</l>
                  <l>With irkſome cries, bewaile thy late doen deede,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe thou loueſt, is ſure thy mortall foe,</l>
                  <l>And helpe for thee, there is none ſure,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill in paine, thou muſt endure,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:5735:43"/>
                  <l>The ſtriken Deare hath helpe, to heale his wounde,</l>
                  <l>The haggerd hauke, with toile is made full tame:</l>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt tower, the Canon laies on grounde,</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt witt, that euer had the fame.</l>
                  <l>Was thrall to Loue, by <hi>Cupids</hi> ſleights,</l>
                  <l>Then waie my caſe with equall waights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She is my ioye, ſhe is my care and wo,</l>
                  <l>She is my paine, ſhe is my eaſe therefore:</l>
                  <l>She is my death, ſhe is my life alſo,</l>
                  <l>She is my ſalue, ſhe is my wounded ſore.</l>
                  <l>In fine, ſhe hath the hande and knife,</l>
                  <l>That maie bothe ſaue, and ende my life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſhal I liue on yearth to be her thral?</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I ſue, and ſerue her all in vaine?</l>
                  <l>And kiſſe the ſtepps, that ſhe letts fall,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I praie the gods, to kepe the pain</l>
                  <l>From her, that is ſo cruell ſtill?</l>
                  <l>No, no, on her woorke all your will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let her feele the power of all your might,</l>
                  <l>And let her haue her moſte deſire with ſpeede:</l>
                  <l>And let her pine awaie, bothe daie and night,</l>
                  <l>And let her moue, and none lament her neede.</l>
                  <l>And let all thoſe, that ſhall her ſe,</l>
                  <l>Diſpiſe her ſtate, and pitie me.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ Not attainyng to his deſire, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Am not as ſeme to bee,</l>
                  <l>Nor when I ſmile, I am not glad:</l>
                  <l>A thrall although you count me free,</l>
                  <l>I moſte in mirthe, moſte penſiue ſadd.</l>
                  <l>I ſmile to ſhade my bitter ſpight,</l>
                  <l>As Haniball that ſawe in ſight:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:5735:43"/>His countrey ſoile, with Carthage
toune:</l>
                  <l>By Romaine force, defaced doune.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And <hi>Caeſar</hi> that preſented was,</l>
                  <l>With noble <hi>Pompeyes</hi> princely hedd,</l>
                  <l>As twere ſome iudge, to rule the caſe,</l>
                  <l>A floud of teares, he ſemde to ſhedd.</l>
                  <l>Although in deede, it ſprong of ioye,</l>
                  <l>Yet others thought it was annoye:</l>
                  <l>Thus contraries be vſed I finde,</l>
                  <l>Of wiſe to cloke the couert minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I <hi>Haniball</hi> that ſmiles for grief,</l>
                  <l>And let you <hi>Caeſars</hi> teares ſuffice:</l>
                  <l>The one that laughs at his miſchief,</l>
                  <l>The other all for ioye that cries.</l>
                  <l>I ſmile to ſee me ſcorned ſo,</l>
                  <l>You wepe for ioye, to ſee me wo:</l>
                  <l>And I a harte by loue ſlaine dead,</l>
                  <l>Preſents in place of <hi>Pompeyes</hi> head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O cruell happ, and harde eſtate,</l>
                  <l>That forceth me to loue my foe:</l>
                  <l>Accurſed be ſo foule afate,</l>
                  <l>My choiſe for to profixe it ſo.</l>
                  <l>So long to fight with ſecret ſore,</l>
                  <l>And finde no ſecret ſalue therefore:</l>
                  <l>Some purge their paine, by plaint I finde,</l>
                  <l>But I in vaine doe breathe my winde.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶His mynde not quietly ſetled, he writeth this.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as the waxe doeth melt, or dewe conſume awaie,</l>
                  <l>Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne, ſo I behold through careful thoughts
decaie:</l>
                  <l>For my beſt lucke leads me, to ſuche ſiniſter
ſtate,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:5735:44"/>That I doe waſt with others loue, that
hath my ſelf in hate.</l>
                  <l>And he that beats the buſhe, the wiſhed birde not
getts,</l>
                  <l>But ſuche I ſee as ſitteth ſtill, and holds the
foulyng netts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Drone more honie ſucks, that laboureth not at all,</l>
                  <l>Then doeth the Bee, to whoſe moſt pain, leaſt pleaſure
doth befall:</l>
                  <l>The Gardner ſowes the ſeeds, whereof the flowers doe
growe,</l>
                  <l>And others yet doe gather them, that tooke leſſe paine I
knowe.</l>
                  <l>So I the pleaſaunt grape haue pulled from the Vine,</l>
                  <l>And yet I languiſh in greate thirſt, while others drinke
the wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus like a wofull wight, I woue my webb of woe,</l>
                  <l>The more I would wede out my cares, the more thei ſeme to
grow</l>
                  <l>The whiche betokeneth hope, forſaken is of me,</l>
                  <l>That with the carefull culuer climes, the worne &amp; withered
tree.</l>
                  <l>To entertaine my thoughts, and there my happe to mone,</l>
                  <l>That neuer am leſſe idle lee, then when I am alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Of the mightie power of Loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY meanyng is to worke, what wondes loue hath wrought,</l>
                  <l>Wherwith I muſe why me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wit, haue loue ſo derely
bought:</l>
                  <l>For loue is worſe then hate, and eke more harme hath
doen,</l>
                  <l>Record I take of thoſe that rede, of Paris Priams
ſonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It ſemed the God of ſlepe had mazed ſo muche his
witts,</l>
                  <l>When he refuſed witt for loue, whiche cometh but by
fitts:</l>
                  <l>But why accuſe I hym, whom yearth hath couered long,</l>
                  <l>There be of his poſteritie aliue, I doe hym wrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whom I might well condempne, to be a cruell iudge:</l>
                  <l>Vnto my ſelf who hath the crime, in others that I
grudge.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>E. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:5735:44"/>
               <head>¶Beyng diſdained, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF frendleſſe faithe, if giltleſſe thought maie
ſhield,</l>
                  <l>If ſimple truthe that neuer ment to ſwerue:</l>
                  <l>If dere deſire accepted frute doe yield,</l>
                  <l>If greedie luſt in loyall life doe ſerue.</l>
                  <l>Then maie my plaint bewaile my heauie harme:</l>
                  <l>That ſekyng calme, haue ſtombled on the ſtorme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My wonted cheare, ecclipſed by the cloude,</l>
                  <l>Of deepe diſdaine, through errour of reporte:</l>
                  <l>If wearie woe enwrapped in thy ſhroude,</l>
                  <l>Lies ſlaine by tonge of the vnfrendly ſorte.</l>
                  <l>Yet heauen and yearth, and all that nature wrought:</l>
                  <l>I call to vowe of my vnſpotted thought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſhade I ſeke in parte, to ſhilde my taint,</l>
                  <l>But ſimple truthe, I hunt no other ſute:</l>
                  <l>On that I gape, the iſſue of my plaint,</l>
                  <l>If that I quaile, let iuſtice me confute.</l>
                  <l>If that my place, emongs the giltles ſort,</l>
                  <l>Repaie by dome, my name and good report.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Goe heauie verſe, perſue deſired grace,</l>
                  <l>Where pittie ſhrinde in cell of ſecret breſt:</l>
                  <l>Awaits my haſt, the rightfull lott to place,</l>
                  <l>And lothes to ſee, the giltles man oppreſt.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues great, haue crouned her more with fame,</l>
                  <l>Then kyngly ſtate, though largely ſhine the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Of the meane estate.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe higher that the Ceder tree, vnder the heauens doe
growe,</l>
                  <l>The more in danger is the top, when ſturdie winds gan
blowe,</l>
                  <l>Who iudges then in princely throne, to be deuoide of hate,</l>
                  <l>Doeth not yet knowe, what heapes of ill, lies hid in ſuche
eſtate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:5735:45"/>Suche dangers greate, ſuche gripes of
minde, ſuche toile doe thei ſuſtaine,</l>
                  <l>That oftentimes, of God thei wiſhe, to be vnkyngde
againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For as the huge &amp; mightie rocks, withſtande the ragyng
ſeas,</l>
                  <l>So kyngdoms in ſubiection be, whereas dame Fortune
pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Of brittle ioye, of ſmilyng cheare, of honie mixt with
gall,</l>
                  <l>Allotted is to euery Prince, in fredome to be thrall.</l>
                  <l>What watches longe, what ſtepps vnſure, what grefes and
cares of minde:</l>
                  <l>What bitter broiles, what endles toiles, to kyngdoms be
aſſingde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſubiect then maie well compare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prince for pleſant
daies,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſilent might bryngs quiet reſt, whoſe might no
ſtorme bewraies:</l>
                  <l>How muche be we, then bounde to God, who ſuche prouiſion
maks</l>
                  <l>To laye our cares vpon the Prince thus doeth he for our
ſaks.</l>
                  <l>To hym therefore, let vs lift vp our harts, and praie a
maine:</l>
                  <l>That euery Prince that he hath plaſt, maie long in quiet
raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Of a contented mynde.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen all is doen and ſaied, in the ende thus ſhall you
finde,</l>
                  <l>The moſte of all doeth bathe in bliſſe, that hath a
quiet minde:</l>
                  <l>And clere from worldly cares, to deame can be content,</l>
                  <l>The ſweteſt tyme, in all his life, in thinkyng to be
ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The bodie ſubiect is, to fickle Fortunes power,</l>
                  <l>And to a million of miſhapps, is caſuall euery hower:</l>
                  <l>And death in tyme doeth chaunge it to a clodde of claye,</l>
                  <l>When as the mynde whiche is deuine, runnes neuer to
decaie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Companion none is like, vnto the mynde alone,</l>
                  <l>For many haue been harmde by ſpeache, through thinking fewe
or none:</l>
                  <l>Fewe oftentymes reſtraineth words, but maks not thoughts to
ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>And he ſpeaks beſt that hath the ſkill, when for to
holde his peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our wealth leaues vs at death, our kinſmen at the graue,</l>
                  <l>But vertues of the mynde, vnto the heauens with vs we
haue:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:5735:45"/>Wherefore for vertues ſake, I can be well
content,</l>
                  <l>The ſweteſt tyme of all my life, to deme in thinkyng
ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Trie before you truſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO counſell my eſtate, abandonde to the ſpoile,</l>
                  <l>Of forged frendes whoſe groſeſt fraude, it ſet with
fineſt foile.</l>
                  <l>To verifie true dealyng wights, whoſe truſt no treaſon
dreads,</l>
                  <l>And all to deare thacquaintance be, of ſuche moſte
harmfull heads.</l>
                  <l>I am aduiſed thus, who ſo doeth frende, frende ſo,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe next he feared, for to become a fo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To haue a fained frende, no perill like I finde,</l>
                  <l>Oft fleryng face maie mantell beſt, a miſchief in the
mynde:</l>
                  <l>A paire of angels eares, oft tymes doeth hide a ſerpents
harte,</l>
                  <l>Vnder whoſe gripes who ſo doeth come, to late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaines
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I doe aduiſe, who ſo doeth frende frende
ſoe,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe next, he ſhould become a mortall
foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Refuſe reſpectyng frends, that courtly knowe to faine,</l>
                  <l>For gold that winnes for gold, ſhall loſe, the ſelf
ſame frend againe:</l>
                  <l>The Quaile needs neuer feare, in foulers netts to fall,</l>
                  <l>If he would neuer bende his eare, to liſten to his call.</l>
                  <l>Therefore truſt not to ſone, but when you frende frende
ſoe,</l>
                  <l>As though to morrowe next, ye feard for to become a foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶ He renounceth all the affectes of loue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke as the Harte that lifteth vp his eares,</l>
                  <l>To heare the hounds, that hath hym in the chafe:</l>
                  <l>Doeth caſt the winde, in daungers and in feares,</l>
                  <l>With fliyng foote, to paſſe awaie apace.</l>
                  <l>So muſt I fly of loue the vaine purſute,</l>
                  <l>Whereof the gaine is leſſer then the friute.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:5735:46"/>
                  <l>And I alſo muſt lothe thoſe learyng looks,</l>
                  <l>Where loue doeth lurke ſtill with a ſubtill ſlaight:</l>
                  <l>With painted mocks, and inward hidden hooks,</l>
                  <l>To trapp by truſt, that lieth not in waite.</l>
                  <l>The ende whereof, aſſaie it who ſo ſhall,</l>
                  <l>Is ſugred ſmart, and inward bitter gall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I alſo muſt flie ſuche Sirian ſongs,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith that Circes, Vliſſes did enchaunt:</l>
                  <l>Theſe wilie Watts I meane, with filed tongs,</l>
                  <l>That harts of ſteele, haue power to daunt,</l>
                  <l>Who ſo as hauke, that ſtoppeth to their call,</l>
                  <l>For moſte deſart, receiueth leaſt of all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But woe to me that firſt behelde thoſe eyes,</l>
                  <l>The trapp wherein I ſaie, that I was tane:</l>
                  <l>An outward ſalue, whiche inward me deſtroies,</l>
                  <l>Whereto I runne, as Ratt vnto her bane.</l>
                  <l>As to the fiſhe, ſometyme it doeth befall,</l>
                  <l>That with the baite, doeth ſwallowe hooke and all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Within my breaſt, wherewith I daiely fedd,</l>
                  <l>The vaine repaſt of amorous hot deſire:</l>
                  <l>With loytryng luſt, ſo long that hath me fedd,</l>
                  <l>Till he hath brought me to the flamyng fire.</l>
                  <l>In tyme at Phenix ends her care and carks,</l>
                  <l>I make the fire, and burne my ſelf with ſparks.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aux.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng in ſorrowe he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MIſtruſt miſdemes amiſſe, whereby diſpleaſure
growes,</l>
                  <l>And time delaied, finds fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds afraied, their faith for to
diſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>Suſpect that breede the thought, and thought to ſighes
conuarte,</l>
                  <l>And ſighs haue ſought a floud of teares, wher ſobbs do
ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:5735:46"/>
                  <l>Thus harte that meanes no harme, muſt feede on ſorrowes
all,</l>
                  <l>Vntill ſuche tyme as pleaſeth the iudge, the truth in
queſtion call:</l>
                  <l>Though cauſe of greate miſtruſt, before that iudge
appeare,</l>
                  <l>My truthe and mercie of my iudge, I truſt ſhall ſet me
cleare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Report theſe rimes at large, my truthe for to detecte,</l>
                  <l>Yet truthe in tyme ſhall trie it ſelf, and driue awaie
ſuſpecte:</l>
                  <l>Beleue not euery ſpeache nor ſpeake not all you heare,</l>
                  <l>For truthe and mercie of the iudge, I truſt ſhall ſet me
cleare.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>L. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng in loue, he complaineth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ENforſt by loue and feare, to pleaſe and not offende,</l>
                  <l>Within the words you would me write, a meſſage muſt I
ſende:</l>
                  <l>A wofull errande ſure a wretched man muſt write,</l>
                  <l>A wretched tale, a wofull head, beſemeth to endite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For what can he but waile, that hath but all he would.</l>
                  <l>And yet that all, is nought at all, but lacke of all he
ſhould:</l>
                  <l>But lacke of all his minde: what can be greater greif,</l>
                  <l>That haue &amp; lacke that likes him beſt, muſt neds be
moſt miſchief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now foole what maks thee waile, yet ſome might ſaie full
well</l>
                  <l>That haſt no harme but of thy ſelf, as thou thy ſelf
canſt tell:</l>
                  <l>To whom I aunſwere thus, ſince all my harmes doe
growe,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my ſelf, ſo of my ſelf, ſome happ maie come I
trowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince I ſee bothe happ, and harme betids to me,</l>
                  <l>For preſent woe, my after bliſſe, will make me not
forget thee:</l>
                  <l>Who hath a field of golde, and maie not come therein,</l>
                  <l>Muſt liue in hope till he haue forſe, his treaſure well
to winne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe ioyes by hope of dreade, to conquere or to loſe,</l>
                  <l>So greate a wealth doeth riſe, and for example doeth
diſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>To winne the golden fleſe, ſtoode Iaſon not in
drede,</l>
                  <l>Till that Medeas hope of helpe, did giue hym hope to
ſpede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:5735:47"/>
                  <l>Yet ſure his minde was muche, and yet his feare the
more,</l>
                  <l>That hath no happ but by your helpe, maie happ for to
reſtore:</l>
                  <l>The ragyng Bulls he dread, yet by his Ladies charme,</l>
                  <l>He knewe it might be brought to paſſe, thei could doe
little harme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnto whoſe grace yelde he, as I doe offer me,</l>
                  <l>Into your hands to haue his happ, not like hym for to be:</l>
                  <l>But as kyng Priamus did binde hym to the will.</l>
                  <l>Of Creſſed falſe whiche hym forſooke, with Diomede to
ſpill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So I to you commende my faithe, and eke my ioye,</l>
                  <l>I hope you will not be ſo falſe, as Creſſed was to
Troye:</l>
                  <l>For if I be vntrue, her Lazares death I wiſhe,</l>
                  <l>And eke to thee if I be falſe, her clapper and her
diſhe.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. L.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng in trouble, he writeth thus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN terrours trapp with thraldome thruſt,</l>
                  <l>Their thornie thoughts to taſt and trie:</l>
                  <l>In conſcience cleare from caſe vniuſt,</l>
                  <l>With carpyng cares did call and crie.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied O God, yet thou art he,</l>
                  <l>That can and will deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus tremblyng there with teares I trodd.</l>
                  <l>To totter tide in truthes defence:</l>
                  <l>With ſighes and ſobbs, I ſaied O God,</l>
                  <l>Let right not haue this recompence.</l>
                  <l>Leſt that my foes might laugh to ſee,</l>
                  <l>That thou wouldeſt not deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſoule then to repentaunce ranne,</l>
                  <l>My ragged clothes berent and torne:</l>
                  <l>And did bewaile the loſſe it wanne,</l>
                  <l>With lothſome life ſo long forlorne.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied O God yet thou art he,</l>
                  <l>That can and will deliuer me. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:5735:47"/>
                  <l>Then comfort came with clothes of ioye</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſemes were faithfull ſtedfaſtneſſe:</l>
                  <l>And did bedecke that naked boye,</l>
                  <l>Whiche erſt was full of wretchedneſſe.</l>
                  <l>And ſaied be glad for God is he,</l>
                  <l>That ſhortly will deliuer thee. <hi>Bis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Beyng troubled in mynde, he writeth as
followeth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe bitter ſweate that ſtraines my yelded harte,</l>
                  <l>The careleſſe count, that doeth the ſame embrace:</l>
                  <l>The doubtfull hope, to reape my due deſarte,</l>
                  <l>The penſiue path, that guids my reſtleſſe race.</l>
                  <l>Are at ſuche warre within my wounded breſt,</l>
                  <l>As doeth bereue my ioye and eke my reſt,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My greedie will, that ſeks the golden gaine,</l>
                  <l>My luckles lot, doeth alwaie take in worthe:</l>
                  <l>My mated mynde, that dredes my ſutes in vaine,</l>
                  <l>My piteous plaint, doeth helpe for to ſet forthe.</l>
                  <l>So that betwene twoo waues of ragyng ſeas,</l>
                  <l>I driue my daies in troubles and deſeaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My wofull eyes doe take their chief delight,</l>
                  <l>To feede their fill vpon the pleaſaunt maze:</l>
                  <l>My hidden harmes that growe in me by ſight,</l>
                  <l>With pinyng paines doe driue me from the gaze.</l>
                  <l>And to my hope I reape no other hire,</l>
                  <l>But burne my ſelf, and I to blowe the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I.H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶Looke or you leape.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF thou in ſuertie ſafe wilt ſitt,</l>
                  <l>If thou delight at reſt to dwell:</l>
                  <l>Spende no more words then ſhall ſeme fitt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:5735:48"/>Let tonge in ſilence talke expell.</l>
                  <l>In all thyngs that thou ſeeſt men bent,</l>
                  <l>Se all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In worldly works degrees are three,</l>
                  <l>Makers, doers, and lookers on:</l>
                  <l>The lookers on haue libertie,</l>
                  <l>Bothe the others to iudge vpon.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore in all, as men are bent,</l>
                  <l>Se all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The makers oft are in fault founde,</l>
                  <l>The doers doubt of praiſe or ſhame:</l>
                  <l>The lookers on finde ſureſt grounde,</l>
                  <l>Thei haue the fruite, yet free from blame.</l>
                  <l>This doeth perſuade in all here ment,</l>
                  <l>Se all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The prouerbe is not South and Weſt,</l>
                  <l>Whiche hath be ſaied, long tyme agoe:</l>
                  <l>Of little medlyng cometh reſt,</l>
                  <l>The buſie man neuer wanteth woe.</l>
                  <l>The beſt waie is in all worlds ſent,</l>
                  <l>Se all, ſaie nought, holde thee content.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Iasper Haywood.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶He bewaileth his miſhappe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN wretched ſtate alas I rewe my life,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſorrowes rage torments with deadly paine:</l>
                  <l>In drowned eyes, beholde my teares be rife,</l>
                  <l>In doubtfull ſtate, a wretche I muſt remaine,</l>
                  <l>You wofull wights enured to like diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Bewaile with me my wofull heauineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſtonie harte ſuche hardnes can retaine,</l>
                  <l>That ſharpe remorſe, no reſt can finde therein:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:5735:48"/>What ruthleſſe eyes ſo careleſſe
can remaine,</l>
                  <l>That daiely teares maie pitie winne.</l>
                  <l>For right I ſeeke, and yet renewe my ſore,</l>
                  <l>Vouchſalfe at length my ſaftie to reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My loue is loſt, woe worthe in woe I dye,</l>
                  <l>Diſdainfull harte doeth worke ſuche hatefull ſpite:</l>
                  <l>In loſſe of loue a wretche muſt ioye to dye,</l>
                  <l>For life is death, now hope is baniſht quite.</l>
                  <l>O death approche bereue my life from me,</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould I liue oppreſt with woe to be.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶The complaint of a Synner.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi> Heauenly God O Father dere, caſt doune thy tender
eye,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a wretche that proſtrate here, before thy trone doeth
lye:</l>
                  <l>O powre thy precious oyle of grace, into my wounded harte,</l>
                  <l>O let the dropps of mercie ſwage, the rigour of my
ſmarte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My fainting ſoule ſuppreſſed ſore, with carefull
clogge of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>In humble ſort ſubmitts it ſelf, thy mercie for to
winne:</l>
                  <l>Graunt mercie then O ſauiour ſwete, to me moſte wofull
thrall,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mornfull crie to thee O Lorde, doeth ſtill for
mercie call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy bleſſed will I haue deſpiſed, vpon a ſtubborne
minde:</l>
                  <l>And to the ſwaie of worldly thyngs, my ſelf I haue
enclinde:</l>
                  <l>Forgettyng heauen, &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly powers, where God and
ſaincts do dwel</l>
                  <l>My life had likt to tread the path, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leads the waie to
hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now my lorde, my lode ſtarre bright I will no more doe
ſo:</l>
                  <l>To thinke vpon my former life, my harte doeth melt for
woe.</l>
                  <l>Alas I ſigh, alas I ſobbe, alas I doe repent:</l>
                  <l>That euer my licencious will, ſo wickedly was bent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sith thus therefore with yernfull plain, I doe thy mercie
craue</l>
                  <l>O Lorde for thy greate mercies ſake, let me thy mercie
haue:</l>
                  <l>Reſtore to life the wretched ſoule, that els is like to
dye,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall my voyce vnto thy name, ſyng praiſe
eternally.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:5735:49"/>
                  <l>Now bleſſed be the Father firſt, and bleſſed be the
Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And bleſſed be the holie Ghoſte, by whom all thyngs are
doen:</l>
                  <l>Bleſſe me O bleſſed Trinitie, with thy eternall
grace,</l>
                  <l>That after death my ſoule maie haue, in heauen a dwellyng
place.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F.K.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>¶The fruite, that ſprynges from wilfull wites, is
ruthe, and ruins rage: And ſure what heedeleſſe youth committes,
repentaunce rues in age.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Rage in reſtleſſe ruthe, and ruins rule my
daies,</l>
               <l>I rue (to late) my rechleſſe youthe, by rules of reaſons
waies:</l>
               <l>I ran ſo long a race, in ſearche of ſureſt waie,</l>
               <l>That leaſure learnde me tread the trace, that led to leud
decaie.</l>
               <l>I gaue ſo large a raine, to vnreſtrained bitt,</l>
               <l>That now with proofe of after paine, I waile my want of
witt:</l>
               <l>I trifeled forthe the tyme, with truſt to ſelf
conceiptes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties vſe prickt forth my prime, to ſearch for
ſugred baites.</l>
               <l>Wherein once learnde to finde, I founde ſo ſweete a
taſte,</l>
               <l>That dewe foreſight of after ſpeede, ſelf will eſtemed
waſte.</l>
               <l>Whiche will, through wilfulneſſe, hath wrought my
witleſſe fall,</l>
               <l>And heedeleſſe youthes vnſkilfulneſſe, hath lapt my
life in thrall.</l>
               <l>Whereby by proofe I knowe, that pleaſure breedeth paine,</l>
               <l>And he that euill ſeede doeth ſowe euill frute muſt reape
againe.</l>
               <l>Let ſuche therefore, whoſe youth, and purſſes are in
Prime,</l>
               <l>Foreſee &amp; ſhun, the helpleſſe ruthe, whiche fews
miſſpence of time.</l>
               <l>For want is nexte to waſte, and ſhame doeth ſynne
enſue,</l>
               <l>Euil ſpeding proofe hath hedeles haſt, my ſelf hath proued
it true.</l>
               <l>When neighbours next houſe burnes, tis tyme thereof take
hede,</l>
               <l>For fortunes whele hath choiſe of turnes, which change of
cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes breds.</l>
               <l>My ſaile hath been aloft, though now I beare but lowe,</l>
               <l>Who clims to high ſelde falleth ſoft, dedſt ebbe hath
higheſt flowe.</l>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ꝙ Yloop.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Henry Diſle, dwellyng at the
Southwest doore of S. Paules Churche. 1576.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5735:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
